{"video_id":"pzmO6RWy1v8","captions":{"sents":["The Islamic State of Iraq and Syria is a phenomenon so terrible and shocking it seems impossible.","It controls an area the size of the United Kingdom, commits mass atrocities, and launches terror attacks abroad.","To understand ISIS, it helps to tell the story of its rise.","That story begins far away and many years before ISIS existed.","In 1979 the Soviet Union invades Afghanistan to defend a puppet dictator against rebels.","Young men from the MidEast flock to join the rebels.","Many see it as a religious struggle, and some develop extremist views.","Among them is a well-educated young Saudi named Osama bin Laden.","Also in Afghanistan is a semi-literate former street thug from Jordan named Abu Musab Zarqawi.","They do not get along, and never will, but will create the groups we today know as al-Qaeda and as ISIS.","The Soviets withdraw in 1989 and the Arab fighters return home.","Bin Laden grows al-Qaeda into a global network, to continue the struggle against Islam's enemies.","Zarqawi forms his own group, but it fizzles.","Both men later return to Afghanistan, now ruled by the Taliban.","On September 11, 2001, al-Qaeda attacks America from its base there.","The US invades Afghanistan and bin Laden flees to Pakistan.","Zarqawi, still obscure, flees to a remote and lawless corner of Iraq.","Two years later, the US does something that will transform the Middle East and set the stage for ISIS: it invades Iraq.","The Americans topple Saddam Hussein's secular, Sunni dictatorship and disbands the Iraqi army.","Thousands of Sunni Iraqi soldiers, angry and unemployed, join the insurgency.","Jihadist groups, also Sunni, see this as a repeat of the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, and again flood in to fight.","Zarqawi is among them.","Zarqawi's group becomes Iraq's most ruthless.","He especially attacks Shia, Iraq's majority, deliberately sparking a Sunni-Shia civil war.","By 2004, Zarqawi is a jihadist superstar.","Al-Qaeda, isolated and weakened, attempts to bolster its image by forming an alliance with Zarqawi's group, which becomes known as al-Qaeda in Iraq.","But in 2006, Iraq's Sunnis rise up against Zarqawi, and the US kills him in an air strike.","Over the next few years al-Qaeda in Iraq is largely defeated.","The Americans withdraw in 2011 from an Iraq that finally looks stable.","In 2011, the Arab Spring spreads across the Middle East.","In Syria, Bashar al-Assad cracks down violently on protesters.","They eventually fire back, leading to civil war.","Assad fears the world will intervene against him.","So he releases jihadists en masse from Syrian prisons, tinging the rebels with extremism and making it harder for foreigners to back them.","Back in Iraq, what little remains of Zarqawi's group is still allied with al-Qaeda but now known as the Islamic State in Iraq.","It's led by a bookish religious scholar who calls himself Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi.","In early 2012, Baghdadi sends a top deputy to Syria to start a new al-Qaeda branch to fight alongside the rebels: Jabhat al-Nusra.","Baghdadi also attacks a series of prisons in Iraq.","They free former jihadists and recruit new ones, growing stronger.","In April 2013, Baghdadi announces he is taking control of all al-Qaeda-allied forces in Syria and Iraq.","His group expands into Syria, becoming the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, or ISIS.","Al-Qaeda rejects Baghdadi's power grab and, in 2014, formally exiles him.","The two jihadist groups, long at odds, are now at war.","ISIS grows powerful in Syria, in part because Assad tolerates its rise, which he does because it divides his enemies within Syria, and foreign powers are too focused on ISIS now to worry about Assad.","By June 2014, ISIS has built an army in Syria, and it launches a military-style invasion into Iraq.","The Iraqi army, weakened by corruption, folds with little fight.","Many Sunnis are tired of their Shia-dominated and increasingly authoritarian government, and welcome or at least tolerate ISIS's arrival.","Within days, ISIS controls a third of Iraq and a big part of Syria.","ISIS's goal is more audacious than anything imagined by al-Qaeda: to revive the ancient Caliphate and expand it to encompass all Muslims.","It earnestly believes its holy war will then bring about the apocalypse as foretold in scripture.","Thousands of Muslims, mostly from the Middle East and from Europe, flock to join the group.","Some join for religious reasons, but many are just disillusioned or angry, and feel that ISIS offers them answers and a purpose.","ISIS quickly overreaches.","That August, it invades Kurdish territory in Iraq and Syria, sparking counter-attacks from better-organized Kurdish forces.","It launches a genocide against Iraqi Yazidis and murders the American journalist James Foley on camera, outraging the world and provoking an American-led air campaign against it.","ISIS is unable to withstand the onslaught, and loses more than a fifth of its territory.","In response, it begins launching increasingly spectacular terror attacks abroad: Kuwait City, Sinai, Beirut, Sousse and then Paris.","So-called lone wolves inspired by ISIS propaganda also launch attacks, though they're often amateurish and less effective.","Eventually, ISIS will lose its state.","It is simply too weak, has no allies or outside funders, and is surrounded by enemies.","But ISIS will respond by reverting to what it was before, as AQI: an insurgency and a terror group still capable of horrifying violence.","In that form, it could be around for years."],"ents":[[["The Islamic State of Iraq","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"]],[["the United Kingdom","GPE"]],[],[],[["1979","DATE"],["the Soviet Union","GPE"],["Afghanistan","GPE"]],[["MidEast","LOC"]],[],[["Saudi","NORP"],["Osama bin Laden","PERSON"]],[["Afghanistan","GPE"],["Jordan","GPE"],["Abu Musab Zarqawi","PERSON"]],[["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["ISIS","ORG"]],[["Soviets","NORP"],["1989","DATE"],["Arab","NORP"]],[["Bin Laden","PERSON"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Islam","ORG"]],[["Zarqawi","PERSON"]],[["Afghanistan","GPE"],["Taliban","ORG"]],[["September 11 , 2001","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["America","GPE"]],[["US","GPE"],["Afghanistan","GPE"],["bin Laden","PERSON"],["Pakistan","GPE"]],[["Zarqawi","PERSON"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Two years later","DATE"],["US","GPE"],["the Middle East","LOC"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Americans","NORP"],["Saddam Hussein 's","PERSON"],["Sunni","NORP"],["Iraqi","NORP"]],[["Thousands","CARDINAL"],["Sunni Iraqi","NORP"]],[["Jihadist","NORP"],["Sunni","NORP"],["Soviet","NORP"],["Afghanistan","GPE"]],[["Zarqawi","PERSON"]],[["Zarqawi","PERSON"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Shia","NORP"],["Iraq","GPE"],["Sunni","NORP"]],[["2004","DATE"],["Zarqawi","PERSON"]],[["Al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Zarqawi","PERSON"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["2006","DATE"],["Iraq","GPE"],["Sunnis","NORP"],["Zarqawi","PERSON"],["US","GPE"]],[["the next few years","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Americans","NORP"],["2011","DATE"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["2011","DATE"],["the Middle East","LOC"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"]],[],[["Assad","PERSON"]],[["Syrian","NORP"]],[["Iraq","GPE"],["Zarqawi","PERSON"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["the Islamic State","ORG"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Abu Bakr al - Baghdadi","PERSON"]],[["early 2012","DATE"],["Baghdadi","PERSON"],["Syria","GPE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Jabhat al - Nusra","PERSON"]],[["Baghdadi","PERSON"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[],[["April 2013","DATE"],["Baghdadi","GPE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["the Islamic State of Iraq","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"]],[["Al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Baghdadi","PERSON"],["2014","DATE"]],[["two","CARDINAL"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"]],[["June 2014","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Iraqi","NORP"]],[["Sunnis","NORP"],["Shia","NORP"]],[["Within days","DATE"],["third","ORDINAL"],["Iraq","GPE"],["Syria","GPE"]],[["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Caliphate","ORG"],["Muslims","NORP"]],[],[["Thousands","CARDINAL"],["Muslims","NORP"],["the Middle East","LOC"],["Europe","LOC"]],[],[],[["August","DATE"],["Kurdish","NORP"],["Iraq","GPE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Kurdish","NORP"]],[["Iraqi","NORP"],["Yazidis","PERSON"],["American","NORP"],["James Foley","PERSON"],["American","NORP"]],[["more than a fifth","CARDINAL"]],[["Kuwait City","GPE"],["Sinai","GPE"],["Beirut","GPE"],["Sousse","PERSON"],["Paris","GPE"]],[],[],[],[["AQI","ORG"]],[["years","DATE"]]],"timestamps":["3.59","9.69","17.199","22.15","26.35","33.57","37.32","41.62","46.11","52.559","60.039","64.71","70.7","70.7","77.039","84.259","84.259","94.45","107.579","114.959","120.619","125.439","129.479","129.479","139.349","143.459","152.26","158.7","162.319","167.379","167.379","177.81","177.81","183.43","191.379","198.9","203.719","213.659","213.659","220.139","227.62","233.159","237.79","242.56","255.579","263.44","266.81","274.93","279.919","288.46","294.199","299.21","306.37","306.37","314.97","326.61","330.569","341.22","349.3","349.3","356.36","365.43"]},"heidel":{"sents":["The Islamic State of Iraq and Syria is a phenomenon so terrible and shocking it seems impossible.","It controls an area the size of the United Kingdom, commits mass atrocities, and launches terror attacks abroad.","To understand ISIS, it helps to tell the story of its rise.","That story begins far away and <TIMEX3 tid=\"t1\" type=\"DURATION\" value=\"PXY\">many years</TIMEX3> before ISIS existed.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t2\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"1979\">1979</TIMEX3> the Soviet Union invades Afghanistan to defend a puppet dictator against rebels.","Young men from the MidEast flock to join the rebels.","Many see it as a religious struggle, and some develop extremist views.","Among them is a well-educated young Saudi named Osama bin Laden.","Also in Afghanistan is a semi-literate former street thug from Jordan named Abu Musab Zarqawi.","They do not get along, and never will, but will create the groups we <TIMEX3 tid=\"t3\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">today</TIMEX3> know as al-Qaeda and as ISIS.","The Soviets withdraw in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t4\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"1989\">1989</TIMEX3> and the Arab fighters return home.","Bin Laden grows al-Qaeda into a global network, to continue the struggle against Islam's enemies.","Zarqawi forms his own group, but it fizzles.","Both men later return to Afghanistan, <TIMEX3 tid=\"t5\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> ruled by the Taliban.","On <TIMEX3 tid=\"t8\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2001-09-11\">September 11, 2001</TIMEX3>, al-Qaeda attacks America from its base there.","The US invades Afghanistan and bin Laden flees to Pakistan.","Zarqawi, still obscure, flees to a remote and lawless corner of Iraq.","<TIMEX3 tid=\"t10\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2003\">Two years later</TIMEX3>, the US does something that will transform the Middle East and set the stage for ISIS: it invades Iraq.","The Americans topple Saddam Hussein's secular, Sunni dictatorship and disbands the Iraqi army.","Thousands of Sunni Iraqi soldiers, angry and unemployed, join the insurgency.","Jihadist groups, also Sunni, see this as a repeat of the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, and again flood in to fight.","Zarqawi is among them.","Zarqawi's group becomes Iraq's most ruthless.","He especially attacks Shia, Iraq's majority, deliberately sparking a Sunni-Shia civil war.","By <TIMEX3 tid=\"t12\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2004\">2004</TIMEX3>, Zarqawi is a jihadist superstar.","Al-Qaeda, isolated and weakened, attempts to bolster its image by forming an alliance with Zarqawi's group, which becomes known as al-Qaeda in Iraq.","But in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t13\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2006\">2006</TIMEX3>, Iraq's Sunnis rise up against Zarqawi, and the US kills him in an air strike.","<TIMEX3 tid=\"t14\" type=\"DURATION\" value=\"PXY\" mod=\"MORE_THAN\">Over the next few years</TIMEX3> al-Qaeda in Iraq is largely defeated.","The Americans withdraw in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t15\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011\">2011</TIMEX3> from an Iraq that finally looks stable.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t16\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011\">2011</TIMEX3>, the Arab <TIMEX3 tid=\"t17\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011-SP\">Spring</TIMEX3> spreads across the Middle East.","In Syria, Bashar al-Assad cracks down violently on protesters.","They eventually fire back, leading to civil war.","Assad fears the world will intervene against him.","So he releases jihadists en masse from Syrian prisons, tinging the rebels with extremism and making it harder for foreigners to back them.","Back in Iraq, what little remains of Zarqawi's group is still allied with al-Qaeda but <TIMEX3 tid=\"t18\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> known as the Islamic State in Iraq.","It's led by a bookish religious scholar who calls himself Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t20\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2012\" mod=\"START\">early 2012</TIMEX3>, Baghdadi sends a top deputy to Syria to start a new al-Qaeda branch to fight alongside the rebels: Jabhat al-Nusra.","Baghdadi also attacks a series of prisons in Iraq.","They free former jihadists and recruit new ones, growing stronger.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t23\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2013-04\">April 2013</TIMEX3>, Baghdadi announces he is taking control of all al-Qaeda-allied forces in Syria and Iraq.","His group expands into Syria, becoming the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, or ISIS.","Al-Qaeda rejects Baghdadi's power grab and, in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t24\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014\">2014</TIMEX3>, formally exiles him.","The two jihadist groups, long at odds, are <TIMEX3 tid=\"t25\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> at war.","ISIS grows powerful in Syria, in part because Assad tolerates its rise, which he does because it divides his enemies within Syria, and foreign powers are too focused on ISIS <TIMEX3 tid=\"t26\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> to worry about Assad.","By <TIMEX3 tid=\"t29\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-06\">June 2014</TIMEX3>, ISIS has built an army in Syria, and it launches a military-style invasion into Iraq.","The Iraqi army, weakened by corruption, folds with little fight.","Many Sunnis are tired of their Shia-dominated and increasingly authoritarian government, and welcome or at least tolerate ISIS's arrival.","Within days, ISIS controls a third of Iraq and a big part of Syria.","ISIS's goal is more audacious than anything imagined by al-Qaeda: to revive the ancient Caliphate and expand it to encompass all Muslims.","It earnestly believes its holy war will then bring about the apocalypse as foretold in scripture.","Thousands of Muslims, mostly from the Middle East and from Europe, flock to join the group.","Some join for religious reasons, but many are just disillusioned or angry, and feel that ISIS offers them answers and a purpose.","ISIS quickly overreaches.","That <TIMEX3 tid=\"t30\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-08\">August</TIMEX3>, it invades Kurdish territory in Iraq and Syria, sparking counter-attacks from better-organized Kurdish forces.","It launches a genocide against Iraqi Yazidis and murders the American journalist James Foley on camera, outraging the world and provoking an American-led air campaign against it.","ISIS is unable to withstand the onslaught, and loses more than a fifth of its territory.","In response, it begins launching increasingly spectacular terror attacks abroad: Kuwait City, Sinai, Beirut, Sousse and then Paris.","So-called lone wolves inspired by ISIS propaganda also launch attacks, though they're often amateurish and less effective.","Eventually, ISIS will lose its state.","It is simply too weak, has no allies or outside funders, and is surrounded by enemies.","But ISIS will respond by reverting to what it was before, as AQI: an insurgency and a terror group still capable of horrifying violence.","In that form, it could be around for years."]},"events":[[],[],[],[],[{"text":"1979","date":"1979","ents":{"item":[["1979","DATE"],["the Soviet Union","GPE"],["Afghanistan","GPE"]],"before":[],"after":[["1979","DATE"],["the Soviet Union","GPE"],["Afghanistan","GPE"],["MidEast","LOC"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"January 1 - United Nations Secretary-General Kurt Waldheim heralds the start of the International Year of the Child. Many musicians donate to the Music for UNICEF Concert fund including ABBA, who write the song \"Chiquitita\" to commemorate the event.","links":["/wiki/United_Nations_Secretary-General","/wiki/Kurt_Waldheim","/wiki/International_Year_of_the_Child","/wiki/Music_for_UNICEF_Concert","/wiki/ABBA","/wiki/Chiquitita"],"ents":[["January 1 - United Nations","DATE"],["Kurt Waldheim","PERSON"],["the International Year","EVENT"],["the Music for UNICEF Concert","ORG"],["ABBA","ORG"],["Chiquitita","PERSON"]]},{"text":"January 1 - The United States and the People's Republic of China establish full diplomatic relations.","links":["/wiki/Sino-American_relations"],"ents":[["January 1 - The United States","DATE"],["the People 's Republic of China","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 1 - The Canton of Jura comes into existence as the 26th canton of Switzerland, being formed from the predominantly French-speaking Catholic part of the Canton of Bern.","links":["/wiki/Canton_of_Jura","/wiki/Cantons_of_Switzerland","/wiki/Catholic_Church","/wiki/Canton_of_Bern"],"ents":[["January 1 - The Canton of Jura","DATE"],["26th","ORDINAL"],["Switzerland","GPE"],["French","LANGUAGE"],["Catholic","NORP"],["the Canton of Bern","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 1 - Following a deal agreed during 1978, French carmaker Peugeot completes a takeover of American manufacturer Chrysler's European operations, which are based in Britain's former Rootes Group factories as well as the former Simca factories in France.","links":["/wiki/France","/wiki/Peugeot","/wiki/Chrysler","/wiki/Chrysler_Europe","/wiki/United_Kingdom","/wiki/Rootes_Group","/wiki/Simca","/wiki/France"],"ents":[["January 1 - Following","DATE"],["1978","DATE"],["French","NORP"],["Peugeot","ORG"],["American","NORP"],["Chrysler","ORG"],["European","NORP"],["Britain","GPE"],["Rootes Group","ORG"],["Simca","ORG"],["France","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 4 – The State of Ohio agrees to pay $675,000 to families of the dead and injured in the Kent State shootings.","links":["/wiki/January_4","/wiki/Ohio","/wiki/Kent_State_shootings"],"ents":[["January 4 –","DATE"],["Ohio","GPE"],["675,000","MONEY"],["Kent State","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 5 – Queen releases \"Don't Stop Me Now\". It becomes one of their most popular singles.","links":["/wiki/January_5","/wiki/Queen_(band)","/wiki/Don%27t_Stop_Me_Now"],"ents":[["January 5 – Queen","DATE"]]},{"text":"January 7 – The People's Army of Vietnam and Vietnamese-backed Cambodian insurgents announce the fall of Phnom Penh, Cambodia, and the collapse of the Pol Pot regime. Pol Pot and the Khmer Rouge retreat west to an area along the Thai border, ending large-scale fighting in the Cambodian–Vietnamese War.","links":["/wiki/January_7","/wiki/People%27s_Army_of_Vietnam","/wiki/Kampuchean_United_Front_for_National_Salvation","/wiki/Phnom_Penh","/wiki/Cambodia","/wiki/Pol_Pot","/wiki/Khmer_Rouge","/wiki/Thailand","/wiki/Cambodian%E2%80%93Vietnamese_War"],"ents":[["January 7 – The People 's Army","DATE"],["Vietnam","GPE"],["Vietnamese","NORP"],["Cambodian","NORP"],["Phnom Penh","GPE"],["Cambodia","GPE"],["Pol Pot","PERSON"],["Pol Pot","PERSON"],["the Khmer Rouge","ORG"],["Thai","NORP"],["the Cambodian – Vietnamese War","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 8 – Whiddy Island Disaster: The French tanker Betelgeuse explodes at the Gulf Oil terminal at Bantry, Ireland; 50 are killed.","links":["/wiki/January_8","/wiki/Whiddy_Island_Disaster","/wiki/Bantry"],"ents":[["January 8 –","DATE"],["French","NORP"],["Betelgeuse","ORG"],["Gulf Oil","ORG"],["Bantry","GPE"],["Ireland","GPE"],["50","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 9 – The Music for UNICEF Concert is held at the United Nations General Assembly to raise money for UNICEF and promote the Year of the Child. It is broadcast the following day in the United States and around the world. Hosted by the Bee Gees, other performers include Donna Summer, ABBA, Rod Stewart and Earth, Wind & Fire. A soundtrack album is later released.","links":["/wiki/January_9","/wiki/Music_for_UNICEF_Concert","/wiki/United_Nations_General_Assembly","/wiki/UNICEF","/wiki/Bee_Gees","/wiki/Donna_Summer","/wiki/ABBA","/wiki/Rod_Stewart","/wiki/Earth,_Wind_%26_Fire"],"ents":[["January 9 –","DATE"],["The Music for UNICEF Concert","ORG"],["the United Nations General Assembly","ORG"],["UNICEF","ORG"],["the Year of the Child","EVENT"],["the following day","DATE"],["the United States","GPE"],["the Bee Gees","ORG"],["Donna Summer","PERSON"],["ABBA","ORG"],["Rod Stewart","PERSON"],["Earth","LOC"],["Wind & Fire","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 16 – Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi flees Iran with his family, relocating to Egypt after a year of turmoil.","links":["/wiki/January_16","/wiki/Mohammad_Reza_Pahlavi","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Egypt"],"ents":[["January 16 –","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["Egypt","GPE"],["a year","DATE"]]},{"text":"January 19 – Former U.S. Attorney General John N. Mitchell is released on parole after 19 months at a federal prison in Alabama.","links":["/wiki/January_19","/wiki/John_N._Mitchell","/wiki/Parole"],"ents":[["January 19 –","DATE"],["U.S.","GPE"],["John N. Mitchell","PERSON"],["19 months","DATE"],["Alabama","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 21 – The Pittsburgh Steelers stake their claim as the NFL team of the 1970s by beating the Dallas Cowboys 35-31 at Miami's Orange Bowl in Super Bowl XIII.","links":["/wiki/January_21","/wiki/Pittsburgh_Steelers","/wiki/NFL","/wiki/1970s","/wiki/Dallas_Cowboys","/wiki/Miami","/wiki/Orange_Bowl","/wiki/Super_Bowl_XIII"],"ents":[["January 21 –","DATE"],["The Pittsburgh Steelers","ORG"],["NFL","ORG"],["the 1970s","DATE"],["Dallas","GPE"],["Cowboys","ORG"],["35 - 31","DATE"],["Miami","GPE"],["Orange Bowl","EVENT"],["Super Bowl XIII","EVENT"]]},{"text":"January 25 – Pope John Paul II arrives in Mexico City for his first visit to Mexico, mainly for 1979's Latin American Episcopal Conference (CELAM) or Conference of Puebla.","links":["/wiki/January_25","/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II","/wiki/Latin_American_Episcopal_Conference","/wiki/Puebla"],"ents":[["January 25 – Pope","DATE"],["John Paul II","PERSON"],["Mexico City","GPE"],["Mexico","GPE"],["1979","DATE"],["Latin American Episcopal Conference","EVENT"],["Conference of Puebla","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 26 – The Dukes of Hazzard debuts on CBS.","links":["/wiki/January_26","/wiki/The_Dukes_of_Hazzard","/wiki/CBS"],"ents":[["January 26 –","DATE"],["CBS","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 29 – Cleveland Elementary School shooting (San Diego): Brenda Ann Spencer opens fire at a school in San Diego, California, killing 2 faculty members and wounding 8 students and a police officer. Her justification for the action, \"I don't like Mondays\", inspires the Boomtown Rats to make a song of the same name.","links":["/wiki/January_29","/wiki/Cleveland_Elementary_School_shooting_(San_Diego)","/wiki/San_Diego","/wiki/The_Boomtown_Rats","/wiki/I_Don%27t_Like_Mondays"],"ents":[["January 29 –","DATE"],["Cleveland Elementary School","ORG"],["San Diego","GPE"],["Brenda Ann Spencer","ORG"],["San Diego","GPE"],["California","GPE"],["2","CARDINAL"],["8","CARDINAL"],["Mondays","DATE"],["Boomtown Rats","PERSON"]]},{"text":"February 1 – Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini returns to Tehran, Iran after nearly 15 years of exile.","links":["/wiki/February_1","/wiki/Ayatollah","/wiki/Ruhollah_Khomeini","/wiki/Tehran","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Exile"],"ents":[["February 1 – Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini","DATE"],["Tehran","GPE"],["Iran","GPE"],["nearly 15 years","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 2 - Former Sex Pistols bassist Sid Vicious is found dead, aged 21, of a heroin overdose in New York City, the day after being released from a 55-day sentence at Rikers Island prison on bail.","links":["/wiki/Sex_Pistols","/wiki/Sid_Vicious","/wiki/Heroin_overdose","/wiki/Rikers_Island"],"ents":[["February 2 - Former","DATE"],["Sid Vicious","PERSON"],["21","DATE"],["New York City","GPE"],["the day","DATE"],["55-day","DATE"],["Rikers Island","LOC"]]},{"text":"February 3 – Ayatollah Khomeini creates the Council of the Islamic Revolution.","links":["/wiki/February_3","/wiki/Council_of_the_Islamic_Revolution"],"ents":[["February 3 –","DATE"],["the Council of the Islamic Revolution","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 7 - Iranian Revolution: Supporters of Ayatollah Khomeini take over the Iranian law enforcement, courts and government administration; the final session of the Iranian National Consultative Assembly is held.","links":["/wiki/Iranian_Revolution","/wiki/Islamic_Consultative_Assembly"],"ents":[["February 7 - Iranian Revolution : Supporters","DATE"],["Ayatollah Khomeini","PERSON"],["Iranian","NORP"],["the Iranian National Consultative Assembly","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 7 - Pluto moves inside Neptune's orbit for the first time since either was known to science.","links":["/wiki/Pluto","/wiki/Neptune"],"ents":[["February 7","DATE"],["Neptune","ORG"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"February 7 - Nazi criminal Josef Mengele suffers a stroke and drowns while swimming in Bertioga, Brazil. His remains are found in 1985.","links":["/wiki/Josef_Mengele","/wiki/Bertioga","/wiki/Brazilian_military_government","/wiki/1985"],"ents":[["February 7","DATE"],["Nazi","NORP"],["Josef Mengele","PERSON"],["Bertioga","GPE"],["Brazil","GPE"],["1985","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 10–11 – Iranian Revolution: The Iranian army withdraws to its barracks leaving power in the hands of Ayatollah Khomeini, ending the Pahlavi dynasty.","links":["/wiki/February_10","/wiki/February_11","/wiki/Ruhollah_Khomeini","/wiki/Pahlavi_dynasty"],"ents":[["February 10–11 – Iranian Revolution","DATE"],["Iranian","NORP"],["Ayatollah Khomeini","PERSON"],["the Pahlavi dynasty","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 12 – Prime Minister Hissène Habré starts the Battle of N'Djamena in an attempt to overthrow Chad's President Félix Malloum.","links":["/wiki/February_12","/wiki/Hiss%C3%A8ne_Habr%C3%A9","/wiki/Chad","/wiki/F%C3%A9lix_Malloum"],"ents":[["February 12 –","DATE"],["Hissène Habré","PERSON"],["the Battle of N'Djamena","EVENT"],["Chad","PERSON"],["Félix Malloum","PERSON"]]},{"text":"February 13 – The Guardian Angels are formed in New York City as an unarmed organization of young crime fighters.","links":["/wiki/February_13","/wiki/Guardian_Angels","/wiki/New_York_City"],"ents":[["February 13 –","DATE"],["New York City","GPE"]]},{"text":"February 13 – The intense February 13, 1979 windstorm strikes western Washington and sinks a 1/2-mile-long section of the Hood Canal Bridge.","links":["/wiki/February_13","/wiki/February_13,_1979_windstorm","/wiki/Washington_(state)","/wiki/Hood_Canal_Bridge"],"ents":[["February 13","DATE"],["February 13 , 1979","DATE"],["Washington","GPE"],["1/2-mile","QUANTITY"],["the Hood Canal Bridge","FAC"]]},{"text":"February 14 - In Kabul, Muslim extremists kidnap the American ambassador to Afghanistan, Adolph Dubs, who is later killed during a gunfight between his kidnappers and police.","links":["/wiki/Kabul","/wiki/Afghanistan","/wiki/Adolph_Dubs"],"ents":[["February 14 -","DATE"],["Kabul","GPE"],["Muslim","NORP"],["American","NORP"],["Afghanistan","GPE"],["Adolph Dubs","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 14 - Following her 1972 sex reassignment surgery, musician Wendy Carlos legally changes her name from Walter. She reveals this information in an interview in the May 1979 issue of Playboy magazine.","links":["/wiki/Sex_reassignment_surgery","/wiki/Wendy_Carlos","/wiki/Playboy"],"ents":[["February 14 - Following her 1972","DATE"],["Wendy Carlos","PERSON"],["Walter","PERSON"],["May 1979","DATE"],["Playboy","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 15 – A suspected gas explosion in a Warsaw bank kills 49.","links":["/wiki/February_15","/wiki/1979_Warsaw_gas_explosion","/wiki/Warsaw"],"ents":[["February 15 –","DATE"],["Warsaw","GPE"],["49","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"February 17 – The People's Republic of China invades northern Vietnam, launching the Sino-Vietnamese War.","links":["/wiki/February_17","/wiki/Vietnam","/wiki/Sino-Vietnamese_War"],"ents":[["February 17","DATE"],["The People 's Republic of China","GPE"],["Vietnam","GPE"],["the Sino - Vietnamese War","EVENT"]]},{"text":"February 18 – The Sahara Desert experiences snow for 30 minutes.","links":["/wiki/February_18","/wiki/Sahara_Desert"],"ents":[["February 18 –","DATE"],["The Sahara Desert","LOC"],["30 minutes","TIME"]]},{"text":"February 20 – This Old House premieres on PBS.","links":["/wiki/February_20","/wiki/This_Old_House","/wiki/PBS"],"ents":[["February 20 –","DATE"],["PBS","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 22 – Saint Lucia becomes independent of the United Kingdom.","links":["/wiki/February_22","/wiki/Saint_Lucia"],"ents":[["February 22 –","DATE"],["Saint Lucia","PERSON"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"]]},{"text":"February 26 - A total solar eclipse, the last visible from the continental United States until 2017, arcs over northern coterminous USA and southeastern Canada ending in Greenland. A partial solar eclipse is visible over almost all of North America and Central America including the eastern half of AK and the western half of UK.[1]","links":["/wiki/Solar_eclipse_of_February_26,_1979","#cite_note-1"],"ents":[["February 26","DATE"],["United States","GPE"],["2017","DATE"],["USA","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Greenland","GPE"],["North America","LOC"],["Central America","LOC"],["half","CARDINAL"],["the western half of UK","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 26 - The Superliner railcar enters revenue service with Amtrak.","links":["/wiki/Superliner_(railcar)","/wiki/Amtrak"],"ents":[["February 26 - The","DATE"],["Superliner","ORG"],["Amtrak","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 27 – The annual Mardi Gras celebration in New Orleans is cancelled due to a strike called by the New Orleans Police Department.","links":["/wiki/February_27","/wiki/Mardi_Gras","/wiki/New_Orleans","/wiki/New_Orleans_Police_Department"],"ents":[["February 27 –","DATE"],["Mardi Gras","PERSON"],["New Orleans","GPE"],["the New Orleans Police Department","ORG"]]},{"text":"March 1 - Scottish devolution referendum: Scotland votes in favour for a Scottish Assembly, which is not implemented due to failing a condition that at least 40% of the electorate must support the proposal; in a Welsh devolution referendum, Wales votes against devolution.","links":["/wiki/Scottish_devolution_referendum,_1979","/wiki/Scotland","/wiki/Welsh_devolution_referendum,_1979","/wiki/Wales"],"ents":[["March 1","DATE"],["Scottish","NORP"],["Scotland","GPE"],["a Scottish Assembly","ORG"],["at least 40 %","PERCENT"],["Welsh","GPE"],["Wales","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 1 - Philips publicly demonstrate a prototype of an optical digital audio disc at a press conference in Eindhoven, Netherlands.","links":["/wiki/Philips","/wiki/Compact_disc","/wiki/Eindhoven"],"ents":[["March 1 - Philips","DATE"],["Eindhoven","GPE"],["Netherlands","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 4 – The U.S. Voyager 1 spaceprobe photos reveal Jupiter's rings.","links":["/wiki/March_4","/wiki/Voyager_1","/wiki/Jupiter%27s_rings"],"ents":[["March 4 –","DATE"],["Voyager 1","PRODUCT"],["Jupiter","LOC"]]},{"text":"March 5 – Voyager 1 makes its closest approach to Jupiter at 172,000 miles.","links":["/wiki/March_5","/wiki/Voyager_1","/wiki/Jupiter"],"ents":[["March 5 – Voyager 1","DATE"],["Jupiter","LOC"],["172,000 miles","QUANTITY"]]},{"text":"March 7 – The largest Magnetar (Soft gamma repeater) event is recorded.","links":["/wiki/March_7","/wiki/Magnetar","/wiki/Soft_gamma_repeater"],"ents":[["March 7","DATE"],["Magnetar","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 8 – Philips demonstrates the compact disc publicly for the first time.","links":["/wiki/March_8","/wiki/Philips","/wiki/Compact_disc"],"ents":[["March 8 – Philips","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 13 – Maurice Bishop leads a successful coup in Grenada. His government will be crushed by American intervention in 1983.","links":["/wiki/March_13","/wiki/Maurice_Bishop","/wiki/Grenada","/wiki/Invasion_of_Grenada","/wiki/1983"],"ents":[["March 13 – Maurice Bishop","DATE"],["Grenada","GPE"],["American","NORP"],["1983","DATE"]]},{"text":"March 14 – In China, a Hawker Siddeley Trident crashes into a factory near Beijing, killing at least 200.","links":["/wiki/March_14","/wiki/Hawker_Siddeley_Trident"],"ents":[["March 14 –","DATE"],["China","GPE"],["Hawker","NORP"],["Trident","PRODUCT"],["Beijing","GPE"],["at least 200","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 16 – End of major hostilities in the Sino-Vietnamese War.","links":["/wiki/March_16","/wiki/Sino-Vietnamese_War"],"ents":[["March 16 –","DATE"],["the Sino - Vietnamese War","EVENT"]]},{"text":"March 17 – The Penmanshiel Tunnel in the U.K. collapses, killing 2 workers.","links":["/wiki/March_17","/wiki/Penmanshiel_Tunnel"],"ents":[["March 17","DATE"],["The Penmanshiel Tunnel in the U.K.","WORK_OF_ART"],["2","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 18 – Ten miners die in a methane gas explosion at Golborne Colliery near Wigan, Greater Manchester, England.[2]","links":["/wiki/March_18","/wiki/Methane","/wiki/Golborne_Colliery","/wiki/Wigan","/wiki/Greater_Manchester","#cite_note-2"],"ents":[["March 18 – Ten","DATE"],["Golborne Colliery","PERSON"],["Wigan","PERSON"],["Greater Manchester","GPE"],["England","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 22 – The NHL votes to approve its merger with the WHA, effective in the fall.","links":["/wiki/March_22","/wiki/National_Hockey_League","/wiki/NHL%E2%80%93WHA_merger","/wiki/World_Hockey_Association"],"ents":[["March 22 –","DATE"],["NHL","ORG"],["WHA","ORG"],["the fall","DATE"]]},{"text":"March 25 – The first fully functional Space Shuttle orbiter, Columbia, is delivered to the Kennedy Space Center, to be prepared for its first launch.","links":["/wiki/March_25","/wiki/Space_Shuttle","/wiki/Space_Shuttle_Columbia","/wiki/Kennedy_Space_Center"],"ents":[["March 25 –","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Space Shuttle","ORG"],["Columbia","ORG"],["the Kennedy Space Center","FAC"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 26 - In a ceremony at the White House, President Anwar Sadat of Egypt and Prime Minister Menachem Begin of Israel sign an Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty.","links":["/wiki/White_House","/wiki/Anwar_Sadat","/wiki/Egypt","/wiki/Menachem_Begin","/wiki/Israel","/wiki/Egypt%E2%80%93Israel_Peace_Treaty"],"ents":[["March 26 -","DATE"],["the White House","FAC"],["Anwar Sadat","PERSON"],["Egypt","GPE"],["Menachem Begin","PERSON"],["Israel","GPE"],["Egypt","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 26 - Michigan State University, led by Earvin \"Magic\" Johnson, defeats Larry Bird-led Indiana State 75-64 in the NCAA tournament championship game at Salt Lake City.","links":["/wiki/Michigan_State_Spartans_men%27s_basketball","/wiki/Magic_Johnson","/wiki/Larry_Bird","/wiki/Indiana_State_Sycamores_men%27s_basketball","/wiki/1979_NCAA_Men%27s_Division_I_Basketball_Tournament","/wiki/1979_NCAA_Men%27s_Division_I_Basketball_Championship_Game","/wiki/Salt_Lake_City"],"ents":[["March 26 - Michigan State University","DATE"],["Earvin \" Magic \" Johnson","PERSON"],["Larry Bird - led","PERSON"],["Indiana","GPE"],["75 - 64","DATE"],["NCAA","ORG"],["Salt Lake City","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 28 - In Britain, James Callaghan's minority Labour government loses a motion of confidence by 1 vote, forcing a general election which is to be held on 3 May.[3]","links":["/wiki/James_Callaghan","/wiki/Labour_Party_(UK)","/wiki/Motion_of_confidence","#cite_note-3"],"ents":[["March 28 - In","DATE"],["Britain","GPE"],["James Callaghan 's","PERSON"],["Labour","ORG"],["1","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 28 - America's most serious nuclear power plant accident occurs, at Three Mile Island, Pennsylvania.","links":["/wiki/Nuclear_power_plant","/wiki/Three_Mile_Island_accident"],"ents":[["March 28 - America 's","DATE"],["Three Mile Island","LOC"],["Pennsylvania","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 29 – Sultan Yahya Petra of Kelantan, the 6th Yang di-Pertuan Agong (Head of State) of Malaysia, dies in office. He is replaced by Sultan Ahmad Shah of Pahang.","links":["/wiki/March_29","/wiki/Yahya_Petra_of_Kelantan","/wiki/Yang_di-Pertuan_Agong","/wiki/Malaysia","/wiki/Ahmad_Shah_of_Pahang"],"ents":[["March 29 – Sultan","DATE"],["Yahya Petra","PERSON"],["Kelantan","GPE"],["6th","ORDINAL"],["Yang","PERSON"],["Malaysia","GPE"],["Sultan Ahmad Shah","PERSON"],["Pahang","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 30 – Airey Neave, World War II veteran and Conservative Northern Ireland spokesman, is killed by an Irish National Liberation Army bomb in the British House of Commons car park.","links":["/wiki/March_30","/wiki/Airey_Neave","/wiki/Northern_Ireland","/wiki/Irish_National_Liberation_Army","/wiki/British_House_of_Commons"],"ents":[["March 30 – Airey Neave","DATE"],["World War II","EVENT"],["Northern Ireland","GPE"],["an Irish National Liberation Army","ORG"],["the British House of Commons","ORG"]]},{"text":"March 31 - The last British soldier (belonging to the Royal Navy) leaves the Maltese Islands, after 179 years of presence. Malta declares its Freedom Day (Jum il-Helsien).","links":["/wiki/Royal_Navy","/wiki/Maltese_Islands","/wiki/Malta"],"ents":[["March 31 - The last","DATE"],["British","NORP"],["the Royal Navy","ORG"],["the Maltese Islands","LOC"],["179 years","DATE"],["Malta","PERSON"],["Freedom Day","EVENT"],["Jum il - Helsien","PERSON"]]},{"text":"March 31 - Gali Atari and Milk and Honey win the Eurovision Song Contest 1979 for Israel, with the song \"Hallelujah\".","links":["/wiki/Eurovision_Song_Contest_1979","/wiki/Israel","/wiki/Hallelujah_(Gali_Atari_and_Milk_%26_Honey_song)"],"ents":[["March 31 - Gali Atari","DATE"],["Honey","PERSON"],["the Eurovision Song Contest","FAC"],["1979","DATE"],["Israel","GPE"],["Hallelujah","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 1 - Iran's government becomes an Islamic Republic by a 98% vote, overthrowing the Shah officially.","links":["/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Islamic_Republic","/wiki/Shah"],"ents":[["April 1 - Iran 's","DATE"],["Islamic Republic","ORG"],["98 %","PERCENT"],["Shah","ORG"]]},{"text":"April 1 - The Pinwheel Network changes its name to Nickelodeon and begins airing on various Warner Cable systems beginning in Buffalo, New York, expanding its audience reach.","links":["/wiki/Nickelodeon"],"ents":[["April 1 -","DATE"],["Nickelodeon","ORG"],["Warner Cable","ORG"],["Buffalo","GPE"],["New York","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 1 – April 18 – Police lock Andreas Mihavecz in a holding cell in Bregenz, Austria and forget about him, leaving him there without food or drink.","links":["/wiki/April_1","/wiki/April_18","/wiki/Andreas_Mihavecz","/wiki/Bregenz"],"ents":[["April 1 – April 18 –","DATE"],["Andreas Mihavecz","PERSON"],["Bregenz","PERSON"],["Austria","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 2 – Sverdlovsk anthrax leak: A Soviet biowarfare laboratory at Sverdlovsk accidentally releases airborne anthrax spores, killing 66 plus an unknown amount of livestock. It is a violation of the Biological Weapons Convention of 1972.","links":["/wiki/April_2","/wiki/Sverdlovsk_anthrax_leak","/wiki/Soviet_Union","/wiki/Biowarfare","/wiki/Yekaterinburg","/wiki/Anthrax","/wiki/Livestock","/wiki/Biological_Weapons_Convention","/wiki/1972"],"ents":[["April 2","DATE"],["Sverdlovsk","GPE"],["Soviet","NORP"],["Sverdlovsk","GPE"],["66","CARDINAL"],["the Biological Weapons Convention of 1972","LAW"]]},{"text":"April 6 – Student protests break out in Nepal.","links":["/wiki/April_6","/wiki/1979_Nepalese_student_protests","/wiki/Nepal"],"ents":[["April 6 – Student","DATE"],["Nepal","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 7 – In Japan, Yoshiyuki Tomino directed Mobile Suit Gundam, the first series of the metaseries of the same name.","links":["/wiki/April_7","/wiki/Yoshiyuki_Tomino","/wiki/Mobile_Suit_Gundam"],"ents":[["April 7 –","DATE"],["Japan","GPE"],["Yoshiyuki Tomino","ORG"],["Mobile Suit Gundam","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"April 10 – A tornado hits Wichita Falls, Texas, killing 42 people (the most notable of 26 tornadoes that day).","links":["/wiki/April_10","/wiki/Wichita_Falls,_Texas","/wiki/1979_Red_River_Valley_tornado_outbreak"],"ents":[["April 10 –","DATE"],["Wichita Falls","PERSON"],["Texas","GPE"],["42","CARDINAL"],["26","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"April 11 – Tanzanian troops take Kampala, the capital of Uganda; Idi Amin flees.","links":["/wiki/April_11","/wiki/Tanzania","/wiki/Kampala","/wiki/Uganda","/wiki/Idi_Amin"],"ents":[["April 11","DATE"],["Tanzanian","NORP"],["Kampala","GPE"],["Uganda","GPE"],["Idi Amin","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 13 – The La Soufrière volcano erupts in St. Vincent and the Grenadines.","links":["/wiki/April_13","/wiki/La_Soufri%C3%A8re_(volcano)","/wiki/St._Vincent_and_the_Grenadines"],"ents":[["April 13 –","DATE"],["St. Vincent and the Grenadines","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 15 – 1979 Montenegro earthquake: A major earthquake (7.0 on the Richter scale) strikes Montenegro (then part of Yugoslavia) and parts of Albania, causing extensive damage to coastal areas and taking 136 lives; the old town of Budva is devastated.","links":["/wiki/April_15","/wiki/1979_Montenegro_earthquake","/wiki/Montenegro","/wiki/Yugoslavia","/wiki/Albania","/wiki/Budva"],"ents":[["April 15 – 1979","DATE"],["Montenegro","GPE"],["7.0","CARDINAL"],["Montenegro","GPE"],["Yugoslavia","GPE"],["Albania","GPE"],["136","CARDINAL"],["Budva","ORG"]]},{"text":"April 17 – Schoolchildren in the Central African Republic are arrested (and around 100 killed) for protesting against compulsory school uniforms. An African judicial commission later determines that Emperor Jean-Bédel Bokassa \"almost certainly\" took part in the massacre.","links":["/wiki/April_17","/wiki/Central_African_Republic","/wiki/School_uniform","/wiki/Jean-B%C3%A9del_Bokassa"],"ents":[["April 17 – Schoolchildren","DATE"],["the Central African Republic","LOC"],["African","NORP"],["Jean - Bédel Bokassa","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 20 – President Jimmy Carter is attacked by a swamp rabbit while fishing in his hometown of Plains, Georgia, USA.","links":["/wiki/April_20","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter_rabbit_incident","/wiki/Fishing","/wiki/Plains,_Georgia"],"ents":[["April 20 –","DATE"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["Plains","GPE"],["Georgia","GPE"],["USA","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 22 – The Albert Einstein Memorial is unveiled at The National Academy of Sciences in Washington, D.C.","links":["/wiki/April_22","/wiki/Albert_Einstein_Memorial","/wiki/National_Academy_of_Sciences"],"ents":[["April 22 –","DATE"],["The National Academy of Sciences","ORG"],["Washington","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 23 – Fighting breaks out in London between the Anti-Nazi League and the Metropolitan Police's Special Patrol Group; protester Blair Peach receives fatal injuries during the incident, now officially attributed to the SPG.","links":["/wiki/April_23","/wiki/Anti-Nazi_League","/wiki/Metropolitan_Police","/wiki/Special_Patrol_Group","/wiki/Blair_Peach"],"ents":[["April 23 –","DATE"],["London","GPE"],["the Anti - Nazi League","ORG"],["the Metropolitan Police 's Special Patrol Group","ORG"],["Blair Peach","PERSON"],["SPG","ORG"]]},{"text":"May 1 – Greenland is granted limited autonomy from Denmark, with its own Parliament sitting in Nuuk.","links":["/wiki/May_1","/wiki/Greenland","/wiki/Parliament_of_Greenland","/wiki/Nuuk"],"ents":[["May 1 – Greenland","DATE"],["Denmark","GPE"],["Parliament","ORG"],["Nuuk","PERSON"]]},{"text":"May 4 – Counting in the previous day's British general election shows that the Conservatives have won and Margaret Thatcher becomes the country's first female prime minister, ending the rule of James Callaghan's Labour government.[4]","links":["/wiki/May_4","/wiki/United_Kingdom_general_election,_1979","/wiki/Conservative_Party_(UK)","/wiki/Margaret_Thatcher","/wiki/James_Callaghan","/wiki/Labour_Party_(UK)","#cite_note-4"],"ents":[["May 4 – Counting","DATE"],["the previous day 's","DATE"],["British","NORP"],["Conservatives","NORP"],["Margaret Thatcher","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["James Callaghan 's","ORG"],["Labour","ORG"]]},{"text":"May 8 – The Woolworth's store in Manchester city centre in England is seriously damaged by fire; 10 shoppers die.","links":["/wiki/May_8","/wiki/F._W._Woolworth_Company","/wiki/Manchester","/wiki/Woolworths_fire"],"ents":[["May 8 –","DATE"],["Woolworth","ORG"],["Manchester","GPE"],["England","GPE"],["10","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"May 9 - The Salvadoran Civil War begins.","links":["/wiki/Salvadoran_Civil_War"],"ents":[["May 9 - The","DATE"],["Civil War","EVENT"]]},{"text":"May 9 - A Unabomber bomb injures Northwestern University graduate student John Harris.","links":["/wiki/Unabomber","/wiki/Northwestern_University"],"ents":[["May 9 - A Unabomber","DATE"],["Northwestern University","ORG"],["John Harris","PERSON"]]},{"text":"May 10 – The Federated States of Micronesia becomes self-governing.","links":["/wiki/May_10","/wiki/Federated_States_of_Micronesia"],"ents":[["May 10 –","DATE"],["The Federated States","GPE"],["Micronesia","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 21 - Dan White receives a light sentence for killing San Francisco Mayor George Moscone and Supervisor Harvey Milk. Gay men in the city riot.","links":["/wiki/Dan_White","/wiki/San_Francisco","/wiki/George_Moscone","/wiki/Harvey_Milk","/wiki/White_Night_riots"],"ents":[["May 21 - Dan White","DATE"],["San Francisco","GPE"],["George Moscone","PERSON"],["Supervisor Harvey Milk","EVENT"],["Gay","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 25 - American Airlines Flight 191: In Chicago, a DC-10 crashes during takeoff at O'Hare International Airport, killing all 271 on board and 2 people on the ground in the deadliest aviation accident in U. S. history.","links":["/wiki/American_Airlines_Flight_191","/wiki/McDonnell_Douglas_DC-10","/wiki/O%27Hare_International_Airport"],"ents":[["May 25 - American Airlines Flight 191","DATE"],["Chicago","GPE"],["DC-10","DATE"],["O'Hare International Airport","FAC"],["271","CARDINAL"],["2","CARDINAL"],["U. S.","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 25 - John Spenkelink is executed in Florida, in the first use of the electric chair in America after the reintroduction of the death penalty in 1976.","links":["/wiki/John_Spenkelink","/wiki/Florida","/wiki/Electric_chair","/wiki/Death_penalty","/wiki/1976"],"ents":[["May 25 - John Spenkelink","DATE"],["Florida","GPE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["America","GPE"],["1976","DATE"]]},{"text":"May 25 - Etan Patz, 6 years old, is kidnapped in New York. He is often referred to as the \"Boy on the Milk Carton\" and the investigation later sprouts into one of the most prolific child abduction cases of all time. This is a cold case until 2010 when it is re-opened. Pedro Hernandez is later charged with strangling him after being sentenced to life in prison for murder and kidnapping in April 2017.","links":["/wiki/Disappearance_of_Etan_Patz"],"ents":[["May 25 - Etan Patz","DATE"],["6 years old","DATE"],["New York","GPE"],["the Milk Carton","ORG"],["2010","DATE"],["Pedro Hernandez","PERSON"],["April 2017","DATE"]]},{"text":"May 27 – Indianapolis 500: Rick Mears wins the race for the first time, and car owner Roger Penske for the second time.","links":["/wiki/May_27","/wiki/1979_Indianapolis_500","/wiki/Rick_Mears","/wiki/Roger_Penske"],"ents":[["May 27 – Indianapolis 500","DATE"],["Rick Mears","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Roger Penske","PERSON"],["second","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"June – McDonald's introduces the Happy Meal.","links":["/wiki/McDonald%27s","/wiki/Happy_Meal"],"ents":[["June – McDonald 's","DATE"]]},{"text":"June 1 - The Vizianagaram district is formed in Andhra Pradesh, India.","links":["/wiki/Vizianagaram_district","/wiki/Andhra_Pradesh"],"ents":[["June 1 - The Vizianagaram","DATE"],["Andhra Pradesh","PERSON"],["India","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 1 - The first black-led government of Rhodesia in 90 years takes power, in succession to Ian Smith and under his power-sharing deal.","links":["/wiki/Rhodesia","/wiki/Ian_Smith"],"ents":[["June 1 - The first","DATE"],["Rhodesia","GPE"],["90 years","DATE"],["Ian Smith","PERSON"]]},{"text":"June 1 - The Seattle SuperSonics win the NBA Championship against the Washington Bullets.","links":["/wiki/Seattle_SuperSonics","/wiki/Washington_Bullets"],"ents":[["June 1 - The Seattle SuperSonics","DATE"],["NBA","ORG"],["Championship","PRODUCT"],["the Washington Bullets","ORG"]]},{"text":"June 2 - Pope John Paul II arrives in his native Poland on his first official, nine-day stay, becoming the first Pope to visit a Communist country. This visit, known as nine days that changed the world, brings about the solidarity of the Polish people against Communism, ultimately leading to the rise of the Solidarity movement.","links":["/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II","/wiki/Communist"],"ents":[["June 2 - Pope","DATE"],["John Paul II","PERSON"],["Poland","GPE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["nine - day","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Communist","NORP"],["nine days","DATE"],["Polish","NORP"],["Solidarity","ORG"]]},{"text":"June 2 - Los Angeles' city council passes the city's first homosexual rights bill signed without fanfare by mayor Thomas Bradley.","links":["/wiki/Los_Angeles","/wiki/Homosexual_rights","/wiki/Tom_Bradley_(American_politician)"],"ents":[["June 2 - Los Angeles '","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Thomas Bradley","PERSON"]]},{"text":"June 3 - A blowout at the Ixtoc I oil well in the southern Gulf of Mexico causes at least 600,000 tons (176,400,000 gallons) of oil to be spilled into the waters, the worst oil spill to date. Some estimate the spill to be 428 million gallons, making it the largest unintentional oil spill until it was surpassed by the Deepwater Horizon oil spill in 2010.","links":["/wiki/Ixtoc_I_oil_spill","/wiki/Gulf_of_Mexico","/wiki/Oil_spill","/wiki/Deepwater_Horizon_oil_spill"],"ents":[["June 3 - A","DATE"],["Ixtoc","PERSON"],["Gulf of Mexico","GPE"],["at least 600,000 tons","QUANTITY"],["176,400,000 gallons","QUANTITY"],["428 million gallons","QUANTITY"],["Horizon","NORP"],["2010","DATE"]]},{"text":"June 3 - General elections are held in Italy.","links":["/wiki/Italian_general_election,_1979"],"ents":[["June 3","DATE"],["Italy","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 4 - Joe Clark becomes Canada's 16th and youngest Prime Minister.","links":["/wiki/Joe_Clark"],"ents":[["June 4 - Joe Clark","DATE"],["Canada","GPE"],["16th","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"June 4 - Flight Lieutenant Jerry Rawlings takes power in Ghana after a military coup in which General Fred Akuffo is overthrown.","links":["/wiki/Flight_Lieutenant","/wiki/Jerry_Rawlings","/wiki/Ghana","/wiki/Coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","/wiki/General_officer","/wiki/Fred_Akuffo"],"ents":[["June 4 - Flight Lieutenant Jerry Rawlings","DATE"],["Ghana","GPE"],["Fred Akuffo","PERSON"]]},{"text":"June 4 - Following the Information Scandal, John Vorster resigns as State President of South Africa.[5]","links":["/wiki/Muldergate_Scandal","/wiki/B._J._Vorster","/wiki/State_President_of_South_Africa","#cite_note-RSA-5"],"ents":[["June 4 - Following the Information Scandal","DATE"],["John Vorster","PERSON"],["State","ORG"],["South Africa","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 7 – The first direct elections to the European Parliament begin, allowing citizens from across all then-9 European Community member states to elect 410 MEPs. It is also the first international election in history.","links":["/wiki/June_7","/wiki/European_Parliament","/wiki/European_Community","/wiki/Member_state_of_the_European_Union","/wiki/Member_of_the_European_Parliament"],"ents":[["June 7 – The","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["the European Parliament","ORG"],["then-9 European Community","ORG"],["410","CARDINAL"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"June 12 – Bryan Allen flies the man-powered Gossamer Albatross across the English Channel.","links":["/wiki/June_12","/wiki/Bryan_Allen_(hang_glider)","/wiki/Gossamer_Albatross","/wiki/English_Channel"],"ents":[["June 12","DATE"],["Bryan Allen","PERSON"],["Gossamer Albatross","PERSON"],["the English Channel","LOC"]]},{"text":"June 18 – Jimmy Carter and Leonid Brezhnev sign the SALT II agreement in Vienna.","links":["/wiki/June_18","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter","/wiki/Leonid_Brezhnev","/wiki/SALT_II","/wiki/Vienna"],"ents":[["June 18 – Jimmy Carter","DATE"],["Leonid Brezhnev","PERSON"],["Vienna","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 19 – Marais Viljoen becomes State President of South Africa.[5]","links":["/wiki/June_19","/wiki/Marais_Viljoen","/wiki/State_President_of_South_Africa","#cite_note-RSA-5"],"ents":[["June 19 – Marais Viljoen","DATE"],["State","ORG"],["South Africa","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 20 – A Nicaraguan National Guard soldier kills ABC TV news correspondent Bill Stewart and his interpreter Juan Espinosa. Other members of the news crew capture the killing on tape.","links":["/wiki/June_20","/wiki/Nicaragua","/wiki/American_Broadcasting_Company","/wiki/Bill_Stewart_(television_journalist)"],"ents":[["June 20 –","DATE"],["Nicaraguan National Guard","ORG"],["ABC TV","ORG"],["Bill Stewart","PERSON"],["Juan Espinosa","PERSON"]]},{"text":"June 22 – The Muppet Movie is released.","links":["/wiki/June_22","/wiki/The_Muppet_Movie"],"ents":[["June 22","DATE"],["Muppet","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 23 – Sydney: New South Wales Premier Neville Wran officially opens the Eastern Suburbs Railway. It operates as a shuttle between Central & Bondi Junction until full integration with the Illawarra Line in 1980.","links":["/wiki/June_23","/wiki/New_South_Wales","/wiki/Neville_Wran","/wiki/Eastern_Suburbs_Railway"],"ents":[["June 23 –","DATE"],["New South Wales","GPE"],["Neville Wran","PERSON"],["the Eastern Suburbs Railway","LOC"],["Central & Bondi Junction","ORG"],["the Illawarra Line","ORG"],["1980","DATE"]]},{"text":"June 24 – Bologna: The Permanent Peoples' Tribunal, an international opinion tribunal, is founded at the initiative of Senator Lelio Basso.","links":["/wiki/June_24","/wiki/Bologna","/wiki/Permanent_Peoples%27_Tribunal","/wiki/Lelio_Basso"],"ents":[["June 24 – Bologna :","DATE"],["The Permanent Peoples ' Tribunal","ORG"],["Lelio Basso","PERSON"]]},{"text":"June 25 – Belgium: NATO Supreme Allied Commander Alexander Haig escapes an assassination attempt by the Baader-Meinhof terrorist organization.","links":["/wiki/June_25","/wiki/NATO","/wiki/Supreme_Allied_Commander","/wiki/Alexander_Haig","/wiki/Red_Army_Faction"],"ents":[["June 25 –","DATE"],["Belgium","GPE"],["NATO","ORG"],["Alexander Haig","PERSON"],["Baader - Meinhof","ORG"]]},{"text":"July 1 - Sweden outlaws corporal punishment in the home.","links":["/wiki/Sweden","/wiki/Corporal_punishment_in_the_home"],"ents":[["July 1 - Sweden","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 1 - The Sony Walkman goes on sale for the first time in Japan.","links":["/wiki/Sony_Walkman"],"ents":[["July 1 - The","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Japan","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 3 – U.S. President Jimmy Carter signs the first directive for secret aid to the opponents of the pro-Soviet regime in Kabul.","links":["/wiki/July_3","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter"],"ents":[["July 3 – U.S.","DATE"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Soviet","NORP"],["Kabul","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 5 – Queen Elizabeth II attends the millennium celebrations of the Isle of Man's Parliament, Tynwald.[6]","links":["/wiki/July_5","/wiki/Elizabeth_II","/wiki/Isle_of_Man","/wiki/Tynwald","#cite_note-6"],"ents":[["July 5 – Queen Elizabeth II","DATE"],["millennium","DATE"],["the Isle of Man 's Parliament","GPE"],["Tynwald","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 8 – Los Angeles passes its gay and lesbian civil rights bill.","links":["/wiki/July_8"],"ents":[["July 8 – Los Angeles","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 9 – A car bomb destroys a Renault owned by Nazi hunters Serge and Beate Klarsfeld at their home in France. A note purportedly from ODESSA claims responsibility.","links":["/wiki/July_9","/wiki/Renault","/wiki/Serge_and_Beate_Klarsfeld","/wiki/ODESSA"],"ents":[["July 9 –","DATE"],["Renault","ORG"],["Nazi","NORP"],["Serge","ORG"],["Klarsfeld","PERSON"],["France","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 11 – NASA's first orbiting space station Skylab begins its return to Earth, after being in orbit for 6 years and 2 months.","links":["/wiki/July_11","/wiki/NASA","/wiki/Skylab","/wiki/Earth"],"ents":[["July 11 –","DATE"],["NASA","ORG"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Skylab","PERSON"],["Earth","LOC"],["6 years","DATE"],["2 months","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 12 - The Gilbert Islands become fully independent of the United Kingdom as Kiribati.","links":["/wiki/Gilbert_Islands","/wiki/Kiribati"],"ents":[["July 12 - The Gilbert Islands","DATE"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"],["Kiribati","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 12 - A Disco Demolition Night publicity stunt goes awry at Comiskey Park, forcing the Chicago White Sox to forfeit their game against the Detroit Tigers.","links":["/wiki/Disco_Demolition_Night","/wiki/Comiskey_Park","/wiki/Chicago_White_Sox","/wiki/Forfeit_(baseball)","/wiki/Detroit_Tigers"],"ents":[["July 12 - A","DATE"],["Comiskey Park","LOC"],["the Chicago White Sox","ORG"],["the Detroit Tigers","ORG"]]},{"text":"July 12 - Carmine Galante, boss of the Bonanno crime family, is assassinated in Brooklyn.","links":["/wiki/Carmine_Galante","/wiki/Bonanno_crime_family","/wiki/Brooklyn"],"ents":[["July 12 - Carmine Galante","DATE"],["Brooklyn","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 12 - A fire at a hotel in Zaragoza, Spain, leaves 72 dead, the worst hotel fire in Europe in decades.","links":["/wiki/Hotel_Corona_de_Arag%C3%B3n_fire","/wiki/Zaragoza"],"ents":[["July 12 - A","DATE"],["Zaragoza","GPE"],["Spain","GPE"],["72","CARDINAL"],["Europe","LOC"],["decades","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 15 – President Jimmy Carter addresses the nation in a televised speech talking about the \"crisis of confidence\" in America today; it would go on to be known as his \"national malaise\" speech.","links":["/wiki/July_15"],"ents":[["July 15 – President","DATE"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["America","GPE"],["today","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 16 – Iraqi President Hasan al-Bakr resigns and Vice President Saddam al-Tikriti replaces him.","links":["/wiki/July_16","/wiki/Iraq","/wiki/Hasan_al-Bakr","/wiki/Saddam_al-Tikriti"],"ents":[["July 16","DATE"],["Iraqi","NORP"],["Hasan al - Bakr","PERSON"],["Saddam al - Tikriti","PERSON"]]},{"text":"July 17 – Nicaraguan dictator General Anastasio Somoza Debayle resigns and flees to Miami.","links":["/wiki/July_17","/wiki/Nicaragua","/wiki/Anastasio_Somoza_Debayle","/wiki/Miami"],"ents":[["July 17","DATE"],["Nicaraguan","NORP"],["Anastasio","PERSON"],["Miami","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 21 - The Sandinista National Liberation Front concludes a successful revolutionary campaign against the U.S.-backed Somoza dictatorship and assumes power in Nicaragua.","links":["/wiki/Sandinista_National_Liberation_Front","/wiki/Nicaragua"],"ents":[["July 21 -","DATE"],["The Sandinista National Liberation Front","ORG"],["U.S","GPE"],["Nicaragua","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 21 - Maria de Lourdes Pintasilgo becomes prime minister of Portugal.","links":["/wiki/Maria_de_Lourdes_Pintasilgo"],"ents":[["July 21 - Maria de Lourdes Pintasilgo","DATE"],["Portugal","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 21 - Maritza Sayalero of Venezuela wins the Miss Universe pageant; the stage collapses after contestants and news photographers rush to her throne.","links":["/wiki/Maritza_Sayalero","/wiki/Venezuela","/wiki/Miss_Universe_1979"],"ents":[["July 21","DATE"],["Sayalero","GPE"],["Venezuela","GPE"],["Universe","ORG"]]},{"text":"July 21 - The Disco music genre dominates and peaks on the Billboard Hot 100 chart, with the first six spots (beginning with Donna Summer's Bad Girls), and seven of the chart's top ten songs ending that week.","links":["/wiki/Disco","/wiki/Billboard_Hot_100","/wiki/Donna_Summer","/wiki/Bad_Girls_(Donna_Summer_song)"],"ents":[["July 21","DATE"],["Disco","GPE"],["100","CARDINAL"],["first","ORDINAL"],["six","CARDINAL"],["Donna Summer 's","PERSON"],["Bad Girls","WORK_OF_ART"],["seven","CARDINAL"],["ten","CARDINAL"],["that week","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 22 – 1979 Ba'ath Party Purge: Iraqi president Saddam Hussein arranges the arrest and later execution of nearly seventy members of his ruling Ba'ath Party.","links":["/wiki/July_22","/wiki/1979_Ba%27ath_Party_Purge","/wiki/Ba%27athist_Iraq","/wiki/Saddam_Hussein","/wiki/Ba%27ath_Party_(Iraqi-dominated_faction)"],"ents":[["July 22 –","DATE"],["Iraqi","NORP"],["Saddam Hussein","PERSON"],["seventy","CARDINAL"],["Ba'ath Party","ORG"]]},{"text":"August 3 – Dictator Francisco Macías Nguema of Equatorial Guinea is overthrown in a bloody coup d'état led by Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo.","links":["/wiki/August_3","/wiki/Francisco_Mac%C3%ADas_Nguema","/wiki/Equatorial_Guinea","/wiki/Coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","/wiki/Teodoro_Obiang_Nguema_Mbasogo"],"ents":[["August 3 – Dictator","DATE"],["Francisco Macías","PERSON"],["Equatorial Guinea","GPE"],["Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo","PERSON"]]},{"text":"August 4 – Opening game of the American Football Bundesliga played between Frankfurter Löwen and Düsseldorf Panther, first-ever league game of American football in Germany.[7]","links":["/wiki/August_4","/wiki/German_Football_League","/wiki/Frankfurter_L%C3%B6wen","/wiki/D%C3%BCsseldorf_Panther","/wiki/American_football","#cite_note-Turn-7"],"ents":[["August 4 – Opening","DATE"],["American","NORP"],["Löwen","PERSON"],["Düsseldorf Panther","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["American","NORP"],["Germany","GPE"]]},{"text":"August 5 – The Polisario Front signs a peace treaty with Mauritania. Mauritania withdraws from the Western Sahara territory it had occupied, and cedes it to the SADR.","links":["/wiki/August_5","/wiki/Polisario_Front","/wiki/Mauritania","/wiki/Western_Sahara","/wiki/SADR"],"ents":[["August 5 –","DATE"],["The Polisario Front","ORG"],["Mauritania","GPE"],["Mauritania","PERSON"],["Western Sahara","LOC"],["SADR","ORG"]]},{"text":"August 8 – Two American commercial divers, Richard Walker and Victor Guiel, die of hypothermia after their diving bell becomes stranded at a depth of over 160 metres (520 ft) in the East Shetland Basin. The legal repercussions of the accident will lead to important safety changes in the diving industry.[8][9]","links":["/wiki/August_8","/wiki/Commercial_diver","/wiki/Hypothermia","/wiki/Diving_bell","/wiki/Wildrake_diving_accident","/wiki/East_Shetland_Basin","#cite_note-Limbrick-8","#cite_note-9"],"ents":[["August 8 – Two","DATE"],["American","NORP"],["Richard Walker","PERSON"],["Victor Guiel","PERSON"],["over 160 metres","QUANTITY"],["520","CARDINAL"],[" ","PERSON"],["the East Shetland Basin","LOC"]]},{"text":"August 9 - A nudist beach is established in Brighton.","links":["/wiki/Nude_beach","/wiki/Brighton"],"ents":[["August 9","DATE"],["Brighton","GPE"]]},{"text":"August 9 - Raymond Washington, co-founder of the Crips, today one of the largest, most notorious gangs in the United States, is killed in a drive-by shooting in Los Angeles (his killers have not yet been identified).","links":["/wiki/Raymond_Washington","/wiki/Crips"],"ents":[["August 9 - Raymond","DATE"],["Washington","GPE"],["the United States","GPE"],["Los Angeles","GPE"]]},{"text":"August 10 – Michael Jackson releases his breakthrough album Off the Wall. It sells 7 million copies in the United States alone, making it a 7x platinum album.","links":["/wiki/August_10","/wiki/Michael_Jackson","/wiki/Off_the_Wall"],"ents":[["August 10 – Michael Jackson","DATE"],["7 million","CARDINAL"],["the United States","GPE"],["7x","ORG"]]},{"text":"August 11 – The former Mauritanian province of Tiris al-Gharbiyya in Western Sahara is annexed by Morocco.","links":["/wiki/August_11","/wiki/Tiris_al-Gharbiyya","/wiki/Western_Sahara","/wiki/Morocco"],"ents":[["August 11 –","DATE"],["Mauritanian","NORP"],["Tiris al - Gharbiyya","PERSON"],["Western Sahara","LOC"],["Morocco","GPE"]]},{"text":"August 14 – A freak storm during the Fastnet Race results in the deaths of 15 sailors.","links":["/wiki/August_14","/wiki/1979_Fastnet_race"],"ents":[["August 14 –","DATE"],["Fastnet Race","ORG"],["15","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"August 27 – Lord Mountbatten of Burma and 3 others are assassinated by the Provisional Irish Republican Army. He was a British admiral, statesman and an uncle of The Duke of Edinburgh. On the same day, the Warrenpoint ambush occurs, killing 18 British soldiers.","links":["/wiki/August_27","/wiki/Louis_Mountbatten,_1st_Earl_Mountbatten_of_Burma","/wiki/Provisional_Irish_Republican_Army","/wiki/Prince_Philip,_Duke_of_Edinburgh","/wiki/Warrenpoint_ambush"],"ents":[["August 27 –","DATE"],["Burma","GPE"],["3","CARDINAL"],["the Provisional Irish Republican Army","ORG"],["British","NORP"],["Edinburgh","GPE"],["the same day","DATE"],["18","CARDINAL"],["British","NORP"]]},{"text":"August 28 – The death toll of the previous day's IRA bombing reaches 5 when Doreen Knatchbull, Baroness Brabourne, 83, dies in a hospital as a result of her injuries.","links":["/wiki/August_28","/wiki/Doreen_Knatchbull,_Baroness_Brabourne"],"ents":[["August 28","DATE"],["the previous day 's","DATE"],["5","CARDINAL"],["Doreen Knatchbull","PERSON"],["Baroness Brabourne","PERSON"],["83","DATE"]]},{"text":"August 29 – A national referendum is held in which Somali voters approve a new liberal constitution, promulgated by President Siad Barre to placate the United States.","links":["/wiki/August_29","/wiki/Somalia","/wiki/Siad_Barre"],"ents":[["August 29 –","DATE"],["Somali","NORP"],["Siad Barre","PERSON"],["the United States","GPE"]]},{"text":"September 1 - The U.S. Pioneer 11 becomes the first spacecraft to visit Saturn, when it passes the planet at a distance of 21,000 km.","links":["/wiki/Pioneer_11","/wiki/Saturn","/wiki/Planet"],"ents":[["September 1 - The","DATE"],["11","CARDINAL"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Saturn","GPE"],["21,000","CARDINAL"],[" ","ORG"]]},{"text":"September 1 - Sri Lanka Army Women's Corps is formed.","links":["/wiki/Sri_Lanka_Army_Women%27s_Corps"],"ents":[["September 1 - Sri Lanka","DATE"],["Women 's Corps","ORG"]]},{"text":"September 7 – The first cable sports channel, ESPN, known as the Entertainment Sports Programming Network, is launched.","links":["/wiki/September_7","/wiki/ESPN"],"ents":[["September 7 –","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["ESPN","ORG"],["the Entertainment Sports Programming Network","ORG"]]},{"text":"September 9 – The long-running comic strip For Better or For Worse begins its run.","links":["/wiki/September_9","/wiki/For_Better_or_For_Worse"],"ents":[["September 9 –","DATE"],["Better or For Worse","ORG"]]},{"text":"September 12 – Hurricane Frederic makes landfall at 10:00 p.m. on Alabama's Gulf Coast.","links":["/wiki/September_12","/wiki/Hurricane_Frederic"],"ents":[["September 12 – Hurricane Frederic","DATE"],["10:00   p.m.","TIME"],["Alabama","GPE"],["Gulf Coast","LOC"]]},{"text":"September 13 – South Africa grants independence to the \"homeland\" of Venda (not recognised outside South Africa.","links":["/wiki/September_13","/wiki/Venda"],"ents":[["September","DATE"],["South Africa","GPE"],["Venda","PERSON"],["South Africa","GPE"]]},{"text":"September 15 – Peter McCormack (Pete the Jakey) Invented the Beefy Bake. This is a reference to Still Game.","links":["/wiki/September_15"],"ents":[["September 15 – Peter McCormack","DATE"],["Pete the Jakey","PERSON"],["the Beefy Bake","WORK_OF_ART"],["Still Game","WORK_OF_ART"]]},{"text":"September 16 – Two families flee from East Germany by balloon.","links":["/wiki/September_16","/wiki/East_Germany"],"ents":[["September","DATE"],["16 –","CARDINAL"],["East Germany","GPE"]]},{"text":"September 20 – French paratroopers help David Dacko to overthrow Bokassa in the Central African Republic.","links":["/wiki/September_20","/wiki/Paratrooper","/wiki/David_Dacko","/wiki/Jean-B%C3%A9del_Bokassa","/wiki/Central_African_Republic"],"ents":[["September","DATE"],["French","NORP"],["David Dacko","PERSON"],["Bokassa","PERSON"],["the Central African Republic","LOC"]]},{"text":"September 22 – The South Atlantic Flash is observed near the Prince Edward Islands, thought to be a nuclear weapons test conducted by South Africa and Israel.","links":["/wiki/September_22","/wiki/South_Atlantic_Flash","/wiki/Prince_Edward_Islands","/wiki/Nuclear_weapons_test","/wiki/South_Africa","/wiki/Israel"],"ents":[["September","DATE"],["The South Atlantic Flash","ORG"],["Prince Edward Islands","GPE"],["South Africa","GPE"],["Israel","GPE"]]},{"text":"September 29 – The dictator Francisco Macias of Equatorial Guinea is shot by soldiers from Western Sahara.","links":["/wiki/September_29","/wiki/Francisco_Macias","/wiki/Equatorial_Guinea","/wiki/Western_Sahara"],"ents":[["September 29","DATE"],["Francisco Macias","PERSON"],["Equatorial Guinea","GPE"],["Western Sahara","LOC"]]},{"text":"September 30 – The Hong Kong MTR begins service with the opening of its Modified Initial System (aka Kwun Tong Line).","links":["/wiki/September_30","/wiki/MTR","/wiki/Modified_Initial_System"],"ents":[["September 30","DATE"],["Hong Kong","GPE"],["MTR","ORG"],["Modified Initial System","FAC"],["Kwun Tong Line","ORG"]]},{"text":"October 1 – Nigeria terminates military rule, and the Second Nigerian Republic is established.","links":["/wiki/October_1","/wiki/Nigeria","/wiki/Second_Nigerian_Republic"],"ents":[["October 1 – Nigeria","DATE"],["the Second Nigerian Republic","ORG"]]},{"text":"October 1 – October 7 – Pope John Paul II visits the United States, starting in Boston.","links":["/wiki/October_1","/wiki/October_7","/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II","/wiki/Boston"],"ents":[["October 1 – October 7 –","DATE"],["John Paul II","PERSON"],["the United States","GPE"],["Boston","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 1 – The MTR, the rapid transit railway system in Hong Kong, opens.","links":["/wiki/October_1","/wiki/MTR","/wiki/Rapid_transit"],"ents":[["October 1 –","DATE"],["MTR","ORG"],["Hong Kong","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 2 – Pope John Paul II arrives in New York City for his first papal tour where he addresses the U.N. General Assembly against all forms of concentration camps and torture.","links":["/wiki/October_2","/wiki/New_York_City","/wiki/U.N._General_Assembly","/wiki/Concentration_camp","/wiki/Torture"],"ents":[["October 2 – Pope","DATE"],["John Paul II","PERSON"],["New York City","GPE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["the U.N. General Assembly","ORG"]]},{"text":"October 3 – An EF4 Tornado hits Windsor Locks, Connecticut, causing extensive damage to the town.","links":["/wiki/October_3","/wiki/EF4","/wiki/Windsor_Locks,_Connecticut"],"ents":[["October 3 –","DATE"],["An EF4 Tornado","ORG"],["Windsor Locks","GPE"],["Connecticut","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 6 – Federal Reserve System changes from an interest rate target policy to a money supply target policy.","links":["/wiki/October_6","/wiki/Federal_Reserve_System"],"ents":[["October 6 – Federal Reserve System","DATE"]]},{"text":"October 7 – Pope John Paul II ends his first U.S. papal visit in Washington, D.C with his first ever visit to the White House.","links":["/wiki/October_7","/wiki/Washington,_D.C","/wiki/White_House"],"ents":[["October 7 – Pope","DATE"],["John Paul II","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["U.S.","GPE"],["Washington , D.C","GPE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["the White House","FAC"]]},{"text":"October 9 – Peter Brock wins the Bathurst 1000 by a record 6 laps, with a lap record on the last lap.","links":["/wiki/October_9","/wiki/Peter_Brock","/wiki/Bathurst_1000"],"ents":[["October 9 – Peter Brock","DATE"],["the Bathurst 1000 by a record","ORG"],["6","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"October 12 - Near Guam, Typhoon Tip reaches a record intensity of 870 millibars, the lowest pressure recorded at sea level. This makes Tip the most powerful tropical cyclone in known world history.","links":["/wiki/Guam","/wiki/Typhoon_Tip","/wiki/Tropical_cyclone"],"ents":[["October 12 - Near Guam","DATE"],["Typhoon Tip","ORG"],["870","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"October 12 - Thorbjörn Fälldin returns as Prime Minister of Sweden, replacing Ola Ullsten who becomes Foreign Minister of Sweden .","links":["/wiki/Thorbj%C3%B6rn_F%C3%A4lldin","/wiki/Prime_Minister_of_Sweden","/wiki/Ola_Ullsten","/wiki/Foreign_Minister_of_Sweden"],"ents":[["October 12 - Thorbjörn","DATE"],["Sweden","GPE"],["Ola Ullsten","PERSON"],["Sweden","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 14 – National March for gay rights takes place in Washington, D.C., involving tens of thousands of people.","links":["/wiki/October_14","/wiki/National_March_on_Washington_for_Lesbian_and_Gay_Rights","/wiki/LGBT_rights_by_country_or_territory","/wiki/Washington,_D.C."],"ents":[["October 14 – National March","DATE"],["Washington","GPE"],["D.C.","GPE"],["tens of thousands","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"October 15 – Black Monday events, in which members of a political group sack a newspaper office, unfold in Malta.","links":["/wiki/October_15","/wiki/Black_Monday_(Malta)"],"ents":[["October 15 – Black Monday","DATE"],["Malta","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 16 – A tsunami in Nice, France kills 23 people.","links":["/wiki/October_16","/wiki/1979_Nice_tsunami"],"ents":[["October 16 –","DATE"],["Nice","GPE"],["France","GPE"],["23","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"October 19 – 13 U.S. Marines die in a fire at Camp Fuji, Japan as a result of Typhoon Tip.[10]","links":["/wiki/October_19","/wiki/Camp_Fuji","#cite_note-10"],"ents":[["October 19 – 13","DATE"],["U.S. Marines","NORP"],["Camp Fuji","LOC"],["Japan","GPE"],["Typhoon","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 20 – The first McDonald's in Singapore opens at Liat Towers in Orchard Road.[11][12]","links":["/wiki/October_20","/wiki/McDonald%27s","/wiki/Singapore","#cite_note-11","#cite_note-12"],"ents":[["October 20 –","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["McDonald 's","ORG"],["Singapore","GPE"],["Liat Towers","ORG"],["Orchard Road","FAC"]]},{"text":"October 26 – Park Chung-hee, the President of South Korea, is assassinated by KCIA director Kim Jae-gyu.","links":["/wiki/October_26","/wiki/Park_Chung-hee","/wiki/President_of_South_Korea","/wiki/KCIA","/wiki/Kim_Jae-gyu"],"ents":[["October 26","DATE"],["South Korea","GPE"],["KCIA","ORG"],["Kim Jae - gyu","PERSON"]]},{"text":"October 27 – Saint Vincent and the Grenadines gains independence from the United Kingdom.","links":["/wiki/October_27","/wiki/Saint_Vincent_and_the_Grenadines"],"ents":[["October 27 –","DATE"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 1 - Military coup in Bolivia.","links":["/wiki/Bolivia"],"ents":[["November 1 - Military","DATE"],["Bolivia","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 1 - Iran hostage crisis: Iranian Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini urges his people to demonstrate on November 4 and to expand attacks on United States and Israeli interests.","links":["/wiki/Iran_hostage_crisis","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Ruhollah_Khomeini","/wiki/November_4","/wiki/Israel"],"ents":[["November 1 - Iran","DATE"],["Iranian","NORP"],["Ayatollah Ruhollah","PERSON"],["Khomeini","PERSON"],["November 4","DATE"],["United States","GPE"],["Israeli","NORP"]]},{"text":"November 2 - French police shoot gangster Jacques Mesrine in Paris.","links":["/wiki/Jacques_Mesrine"],"ents":[["November 2 -","DATE"],["French","NORP"],["Jacques Mesrine","PERSON"],["Paris","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 2 - Assata Shakur (née Joanne Chesimard), a former member of the Black Panther Party and Black Liberation Army, escapes from a New York prison to Cuba, where she remains under political asylum.","links":["/wiki/Assata_Shakur"],"ents":[["November 2 - Assata Shakur","DATE"],["the Black Panther Party","ORG"],["Black Liberation Army","ORG"],["New York","GPE"],["Cuba","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 3 – In Greensboro, North Carolina, 5 members of the Communist Workers Party are shot to death and 7 are wounded by a group of Klansmen and neo-Nazis, during a \"Death to the Klan\" rally.","links":["/wiki/November_3","/wiki/Greensboro,_North_Carolina","/wiki/Communist_Workers%27_Party_(United_States)","/wiki/Ku_Klux_Klan","/wiki/Neo-Nazis"],"ents":[["November 3 –","DATE"],["Greensboro","GPE"],["North Carolina","GPE"],["5","CARDINAL"],["the Communist Workers Party","ORG"],["7","CARDINAL"],["Klansmen","GPE"],["Nazis","NORP"],["a \" Death to the Klan \"","EVENT"]]},{"text":"November 4 – Iran hostage crisis begins: 500 Iranian radicals, mostly students, invade the U.S. Embassy in Tehran and take 90 hostages (53 of whom are American). They demand that the United States send the former Shah of Iran back to stand trial.","links":["/wiki/November_4","/wiki/Iran_hostage_crisis","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Tehran","/wiki/Mohammad_Reza_Pahlavi"],"ents":[["November 4 – Iran","DATE"],["500","CARDINAL"],["Iranian","NORP"],["the U.S. Embassy","ORG"],["Tehran","GPE"],["90","CARDINAL"],["53","CARDINAL"],["American","NORP"],["the United States","GPE"],["Iran","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 5 - All Saints' Massacre: The military junta in Bolivia initiates a violent crack-down on its opponents.","links":["/wiki/All_Saints%27_Massacre","/wiki/Bolivia"],"ents":[["November 5 - All Saints ' Massacre","DATE"],["Bolivia","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 5 - The radio news program Morning Edition premieres on National Public Radio in the United States.","links":["/wiki/Morning_Edition","/wiki/National_Public_Radio"],"ents":[["November 5 -","DATE"],["Morning Edition","WORK_OF_ART"],["National Public Radio","ORG"],["the United States","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 6 – At Montevideo, Uruguay, the International Olympic Committee adopts a resolution, whereby Taiwan Olympic and sports teams will participate with the name Chinese Taipei in future Olympic Games and international sports tournaments and championships.","links":["/wiki/November_6","/wiki/Montevideo","/wiki/Uruguay","/wiki/International_Olympic_Committee","/wiki/Taiwan","/wiki/Chinese_Taipei","/wiki/Olympic_Games"],"ents":[["November 6 –","DATE"],["Uruguay","GPE"],["the International Olympic Committee","ORG"],["Taiwan Olympic","ORG"],["Chinese","NORP"],["Taipei","GPE"],["Olympic Games","EVENT"]]},{"text":"November 7 – U.S. Senator Ted Kennedy announces that he will challenge President Jimmy Carter for the 1980 Democratic presidential nomination.","links":["/wiki/November_7","/wiki/Ted_Kennedy","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter","/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)"],"ents":[["November 7 – U.S.","DATE"],["Ted Kennedy","PERSON"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["1980","DATE"],["Democratic","NORP"]]},{"text":"November 9 - The Carl Bridgewater murder trial ends in England with all 4 men found guilty. James Robinson, 45, and 25-year-old Vincent Hickey are sentenced to life imprisonment with a recommended 25-year minimum for murder. 18-year-old Michael Hickey is also found guilty of murder and sentenced to indefinite detention. Patrick Molloy, 53, is found guilty on a lesser charge of manslaughter and sentenced to 12 years in prison.[13]","links":["/wiki/Carl_Bridgewater","#cite_note-13"],"ents":[["November 9 - The","DATE"],["Carl Bridgewater","PERSON"],["England","GPE"],["4","CARDINAL"],["James Robinson","PERSON"],["45","DATE"],["Vincent Hickey","PERSON"],["Michael Hickey","PERSON"],["Patrick Molloy","PERSON"],["53","DATE"],["12 years","DATE"]]},{"text":"November 9 - Nuclear false alarm: the NORAD computers and the Alternate National Military Command Center in Fort Ritchie, Maryland, detect an apparent massive Soviet nuclear strike. After reviewing the raw data from satellites and checking the early-warning radars, the alert is cancelled.[14]","links":["/wiki/False_alarm","/wiki/NORAD","/wiki/Fort_Ritchie,_Maryland","/wiki/Soviet_Union","/wiki/Nuclear_warfare","/wiki/Early-warning_radar","#cite_note-14"],"ents":[["November 9 - Nuclear","DATE"],["NORAD","ORG"],["the Alternate National Military Command Center","ORG"],["Fort Ritchie","GPE"],["Maryland","GPE"],["Soviet","NORP"]]},{"text":"November 10 – 1979 Mississauga train derailment: A 106-car Canadian Pacific freight train carrying explosive and poisonous chemicals from Windsor, Ontario, Canada derails in Mississauga, Ontario, Canada just west of Toronto, Ontario, Canada, causing a massive explosion and the largest peacetime evacuation in Canadian history and one of the largest in North American history.","links":["/wiki/November_10","/wiki/1979_Mississauga_train_derailment"],"ents":[["November 10 – 1979","DATE"],["Canadian Pacific","ORG"],["Windsor , Ontario","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Mississauga","GPE"],["Ontario","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Toronto","GPE"],["Ontario","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Canadian","NORP"],["one","CARDINAL"],["North American","NORP"]]},{"text":"November 12 - Iran hostage crisis: In response to the hostage situation in Tehran, U.S. President Jimmy Carter orders a halt to all oil imports into the United States from Iran.","links":["/wiki/Iran_hostage_crisis","/wiki/Tehran","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter","/wiki/Petroleum","/wiki/Iran"],"ents":[["November 12 - Iran","DATE"],["Tehran","GPE"],["U.S.","GPE"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["the United States","GPE"],["Iran","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 12 - Süleyman Demirel, of the Justice Party (AP) forms the new government of Turkey (43rd government, a minority government).","links":["/wiki/S%C3%BCleyman_Demirel","/wiki/Justice_Party_(Turkey)","/wiki/Turkey"],"ents":[["November 12 - Süleyman Demirel","DATE"],["the Justice Party","ORG"],["AP","ORG"],["Turkey","GPE"],["43rd","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"November 14 – Iran hostage crisis: U.S. President Jimmy Carter issues Executive Order 12170, freezing all Iranian assets in the United States and U.S. banks in response to the hostage crisis.","links":["/wiki/November_14","/wiki/Iran_hostage_crisis","/wiki/Jimmy_Carter","/wiki/Executive_Order_12170","/wiki/Iran"],"ents":[["November 14 – Iran","DATE"],["U.S.","GPE"],["Jimmy Carter","PERSON"],["Executive Order 12170","ORG"],["Iranian","NORP"],["the United States","GPE"],["U.S.","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 15 – British art historian and former Surveyor of the Queen's Pictures Anthony Blunt's role as the \"fourth man\" of the 'Cambridge Five' double agents for the Soviet NKVD during World War II is revealed by Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher in the House of Commons of the United Kingdom;[15] she gives further details on November 21.[16]","links":["/wiki/November_15","/wiki/Surveyor_of_the_Queen%27s_Pictures","/wiki/Anthony_Blunt","/wiki/Cambridge_Five","/wiki/Double_agent","/wiki/Soviet_Union","/wiki/NKVD","/wiki/World_War_II","/wiki/Prime_Minister_of_the_United_Kingdom","/wiki/Margaret_Thatcher","/wiki/House_of_Commons_of_the_United_Kingdom","#cite_note-15","#cite_note-16"],"ents":[["November 15 – British","DATE"],["Surveyor","ORG"],["the Queen 's Pictures","ORG"],["Anthony Blunt 's","PERSON"],["fourth","ORDINAL"],["Cambridge Five '","FAC"],["Soviet","NORP"],["NKVD","ORG"],["World War II","EVENT"],["Margaret Thatcher","PERSON"],["the House of Commons of the United Kingdom","ORG"],["November 21","DATE"]]},{"text":"November 16 – Bucharest Metro Line One is opened, in Bucharest, Romania (from Timpuri Noi to Semanatoarea stations, 8.63 km).","links":["/wiki/November_16","/wiki/Bucharest_Metro","/wiki/Bucharest","/wiki/Romania"],"ents":[["November 16 –","DATE"],["One","CARDINAL"],["Bucharest","GPE"],["Romania","GPE"],["Timpuri Noi","PERSON"],["Semanatoarea","GPE"],["8.63","CARDINAL"],[" ","ORG"]]},{"text":"November 17 – Iran hostage crisis: Iranian leader Ruhollah Khomeini orders the release of 13 female and African American hostages being held at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran.","links":["/wiki/November_17","/wiki/Iran_hostage_crisis","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Ruhollah_Khomeini","/wiki/African_American","/wiki/Tehran"],"ents":[["November 17 –","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["Iranian","NORP"],["Ruhollah Khomeini","PERSON"],["13","CARDINAL"],["African American","NORP"],["the U.S. Embassy","FAC"],["Tehran","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 20 – Grand Mosque seizure: A group of 200 Juhayman al-Otaybi militants occupy Mecca's Masjid al-Haram, the holiest place in Islam. They are driven out by French commandos (allowed into the city under these special circumstances despite their being non-Muslims) after bloody fighting that leaves 250 people dead and 600 wounded.","links":["/wiki/November_20","/wiki/Grand_Mosque_seizure","/wiki/Juhayman_al-Otaybi","/wiki/Mecca","/wiki/Masjid_al-Haram"],"ents":[["November 20 –","DATE"],["200","CARDINAL"],["Juhayman al - Otaybi","PERSON"],["Mecca","GPE"],["Masjid al - Haram","FAC"],["Islam","ORG"],["French","NORP"],["Muslims","NORP"],["250","CARDINAL"],["600","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"November 21 – After false radio reports from the Ayatollah Khomeini that the Americans had occupied the Grand Mosque in Mecca, the United States Embassy in Islamabad, Pakistan is attacked by a mob and set afire, killing 4, and disturbing Pakistan–United States relations.","links":["/wiki/November_21","/wiki/Ayatollah_Khomeini","/wiki/Grand_Mosque_Seizure","/wiki/Al-Masjid_al-Haram","/wiki/Mecca","/wiki/Islamabad","/wiki/Pakistan%E2%80%93United_States_relations"],"ents":[["November 21 –","DATE"],["Americans","NORP"],["the Grand Mosque","FAC"],["Mecca","GPE"],["the United States Embassy","ORG"],["Islamabad","GPE"],["Pakistan","GPE"],["4","CARDINAL"],["Pakistan","GPE"],["United States","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 23 – In Dublin, Ireland, Provisional Irish Republican Army member Thomas McMahon is sentenced to life in prison for the assassination of Lord Mountbatten of Burma.","links":["/wiki/November_23","/wiki/Dublin","/wiki/Provisional_Irish_Republican_Army","/wiki/Thomas_McMahon_(Irish_republican)","/wiki/Louis_Mountbatten,_1st_Earl_Mountbatten_of_Burma"],"ents":[["November 23 –","DATE"],["Dublin","GPE"],["Ireland","GPE"],["Provisional Irish Republican Army","ORG"],["Thomas McMahon","PERSON"],["Mountbatten","PERSON"],["Burma","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 25 – Last cargo of phosphate shipped from Banaba Island.","links":["/wiki/November_25","/wiki/Phosphate","/wiki/Banaba_Island"],"ents":[["November 25 –","DATE"],["Banaba Island","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 28 – Air New Zealand Flight 901: an Air New Zealand DC-10 crashes into Mount Erebus in Antarctica on a sightseeing trip, killing all 257 people on board.","links":["/wiki/November_28","/wiki/Air_New_Zealand_Flight_901","/wiki/Air_New_Zealand","/wiki/McDonnell_Douglas_DC-10","/wiki/Mount_Erebus"],"ents":[["November 28","DATE"],["901","CARDINAL"],["Air New","ORG"],["DC-10","DATE"],["Mount Erebus","LOC"],["Antarctica","LOC"],["257","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"November 30 – The Wall, a rock opera and concept album by Pink Floyd, is first released.","links":["/wiki/November_30","/wiki/The_Wall","/wiki/Rock_opera","/wiki/Concept_album","/wiki/Pink_Floyd"],"ents":[["November 30 –","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"]]},{"text":"December 3 - The Who concert disaster: eleven fans are killed during a crowd crush for unreserved seats before The Who rock concert at the Riverfront Coliseum in Cincinnati.","links":["/wiki/The_Who_concert_disaster","/wiki/The_Who","/wiki/Riverfront_Coliseum","/wiki/Cincinnati"],"ents":[["December 3","DATE"],["eleven","CARDINAL"],["the Riverfront Coliseum","FAC"],["Cincinnati","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 3 - The United States dollar exchange rate with the Deutsche Mark falls to 1.7079 DM, the all-time low so far; this record is not broken until November 5, 1987.","links":["/wiki/United_States_dollar","/wiki/Exchange_rate","/wiki/Deutsche_Mark","/wiki/1987"],"ents":[["December 3 - The","DATE"],["United States","GPE"],["Deutsche Mark","ORG"],["1.7079","CARDINAL"],["November 5 , 1987","DATE"]]},{"text":"December 3 - Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini becomes the first Supreme Leader of Iran.","links":["/wiki/Ruhollah_Khomeini"],"ents":[["December 3 - Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Iran","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 4 – The Hastie fire in Kingston upon Hull, England, leads to the deaths of 3 boys and begins the hunt for Bruce George Peter Lee, the UK's most prolific killer.","links":["/wiki/December_4","/wiki/Kingston_upon_Hull","/wiki/Bruce_George_Peter_Lee"],"ents":[["December 4 –","DATE"],["Kingston","GPE"],["Hull","GPE"],["England","GPE"],["3","CARDINAL"],["Bruce George Peter Lee","PERSON"],["UK","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 5 – Jack Lynch resigns as Taoiseach of the Republic of Ireland; he is succeeded by Charles Haughey.","links":["/wiki/December_5","/wiki/Jack_Lynch","/wiki/Taoiseach","/wiki/Charles_Haughey"],"ents":[["December 5 – Jack Lynch","DATE"],["Taoiseach of the Republic of Ireland","ORG"],["Charles Haughey","PERSON"]]},{"text":"December 6 – The world premiere of Star Trek: The Motion Picture is held at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C.","links":["/wiki/December_6","/wiki/Star_Trek:_The_Motion_Picture","/wiki/Smithsonian_Institution"],"ents":[["December 6 –","DATE"],["Star Trek","WORK_OF_ART"],["The Motion Picture","WORK_OF_ART"],["the Smithsonian Institution","ORG"],["Washington","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 9 – The eradication of the smallpox virus is certified, making smallpox the first of only two human diseases that have been driven to extinction (rinderpest in 2011 being the other).","links":["/wiki/December_9","/wiki/Smallpox","/wiki/Virus","/wiki/Rinderpest"],"ents":[["December 9 –","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["only two","CARDINAL"],["2011","DATE"]]},{"text":"December 12 - The 8.2 Mw Tumaco earthquake shakes Colombia and Ecuador with a maximum Mercalli intensity of IX (Violent), killing 300–600, and generating a large tsunami.","links":["/wiki/Seismic_scale#Mw","/wiki/1979_Tumaco_earthquake","/wiki/Colombia","/wiki/Ecuador","/wiki/Mercalli_intensity_scale"],"ents":[["December 12 - The","DATE"],["8.2","CARDINAL"],["Mw Tumaco","PERSON"],["Colombia","GPE"],["Ecuador","GPE"],["Mercalli","PERSON"],["IX ( Violent","ORG"],["300–600","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"December 12 - Coup d'état of December Twelfth: South Korean Army Major General Chun Doo-hwan orders the arrest of Army Chief of Staff General Jeong Seung-hwa without authorization from President Choi Kyu-hah, alleging involvement in the assassination of ex-President Park Chung-hee.","links":["/wiki/Coup_d%27%C3%A9tat_of_December_Twelfth","/wiki/South_Korean_Army","/wiki/Chun_Doo-hwan","/wiki/Jeong_Seung-hwa","/wiki/Choi_Kyu-hah","/wiki/Park_Chung-hee"],"ents":[["December 12 - Coup d'état of December Twelfth","DATE"],["South Korean Army","ORG"],["Chun Doo - hwan","PERSON"],["Army","ORG"],["Jeong Seung - hwa","PERSON"],["Choi Kyu - hah","PERSON"],["Park Chung - hee","PERSON"]]},{"text":"December 12 - The unrecognised state of Zimbabwe-Rhodesia returns to British control and resumes using the name Southern Rhodesia.","links":["/wiki/Zimbabwe-Rhodesia","/wiki/Southern_Rhodesia"],"ents":[["December 12 - The","DATE"],["Zimbabwe","GPE"],["Rhodesia","GPE"],["British","NORP"],["Southern Rhodesia","LOC"]]},{"text":"December 15 – The directorial debut of Hayao Miyazaki, The Castle of Cagliostro based on the manga series Lupin III is released in Japan.","links":["/wiki/December_15","/wiki/Hayao_Miyazaki","/wiki/The_Castle_of_Cagliostro","/wiki/Manga","/wiki/Lupin_III"],"ents":[["December 15","DATE"],["Hayao Miyazaki","PERSON"],["The Castle of Cagliostro","ORG"],["Lupin III","PRODUCT"],["Japan","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 21 – A ceasefire for Rhodesia is signed at London.","links":["/wiki/December_21","/wiki/Ceasefire","/wiki/Rhodesia"],"ents":[["December 21","DATE"],["Rhodesia","LOC"],["London","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 23 – The highest aerial tramway in Europe, the Klein Matterhorn, opens.","links":["/wiki/December_23","/wiki/Klein_Matterhorn"],"ents":[["December 23 –","DATE"],["Europe","LOC"],["the Klein Matterhorn","ORG"]]},{"text":"December 24 - The Soviet Union invades Afghanistan, and Babrak Karmal replaces overthrown and executed President Hafizullah Amin, which begins the war.","links":["/wiki/Soviet_Union","/wiki/Soviet_war_in_Afghanistan","/wiki/Babrak_Karmal","/wiki/Hafizullah_Amin"],"ents":[["December 24","DATE"],["The Soviet Union","GPE"],["Afghanistan","GPE"],["Babrak Karmal","PERSON"],["Hafizullah Amin","PERSON"]]},{"text":"December 24 - The first European Ariane rocket is launched.","links":["/wiki/Ariane_1"],"ents":[["December 24 - The first","DATE"]]},{"text":"December 26 – In Rhodesia, 96 Patriotic Front guerrillas enter the capital Salisbury to monitor a ceasefire that begins December 28.","links":["/wiki/December_26","/wiki/Rhodesia","/wiki/Harare","/wiki/December_28"],"ents":[["December 26 –","DATE"],["Rhodesia","GPE"],["96","CARDINAL"],["Patriotic Front","ORG"],["Salisbury","GPE"],["December 28","DATE"]]}],"match":null,"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0.16666666666666666,0.14285714285714285],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0.2,0.16666666666666666],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[],[],[],[{"text":"today","date":"PRESENT_REF","ents":{"item":[["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["ISIS","ORG"]],"before":[["Afghanistan","GPE"],["Jordan","GPE"],["Abu Musab Zarqawi","PERSON"]],"after":[["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["ISIS","ORG"],["Soviets","NORP"],["1989","DATE"],["Arab","NORP"]]},"wiki":[]}],[{"text":"1989","date":"1989","ents":{"item":[["Soviets","NORP"],["1989","DATE"],["Arab","NORP"]],"before":[["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["ISIS","ORG"]],"after":[["Soviets","NORP"],["1989","DATE"],["Arab","NORP"],["Bin Laden","PERSON"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Islam","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"January 2 – Prime Minister Ranasinghe Premadasa takes office as the third President of Sri Lanka.","links":["/wiki/January_2","/wiki/Prime_Minister_of_Sri_Lanka","/wiki/Ranasinghe_Premadasa","/wiki/President_of_Sri_Lanka"],"ents":[["January 2 – Prime Minister Ranasinghe Premadasa","DATE"],["third","ORDINAL"],["Sri Lanka","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 4 – Gulf of Sidra incident (1989): Two Libyan MiG-23 \"Floggers\" are engaged and shot down by 2 US Navy F-14 Tomcats.","links":["/wiki/January_4","/wiki/Gulf_of_Sidra_incident_(1989)","/wiki/Libya","/wiki/Mikoyan-Gurevich_MiG-23","/wiki/F-14_Tomcat"],"ents":[["January 4 – Gulf","DATE"],["1989","DATE"],["Two","CARDINAL"],["Libyan","NORP"],["2","CARDINAL"],["US Navy","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 7 – Hirohito dies, and Akihito is enthroned as the 125th Emperor of Japan immediately, followed by the change in the era name from Showa to Heisei on the following day.","links":["/wiki/January_7","/wiki/Hirohito","/wiki/Akihito","/wiki/Emperor_of_Japan","/wiki/Sh%C5%8Dwa_period","/wiki/Heisei_period"],"ents":[["January 7 – Hirohito","DATE"],["Akihito","PERSON"],["Japan","GPE"],["Showa","GPE"],["Heisei","PERSON"],["the following day","DATE"]]},{"text":"January 8 – Kegworth air disaster: A British Midland Boeing 737 crashes on approach to East Midlands Airport, leaving 47 dead.","links":["/wiki/January_8","/wiki/Kegworth_air_disaster","/wiki/British_Midland","/wiki/Boeing_737","/wiki/East_Midlands_Airport"],"ents":[["January 8 – Kegworth","DATE"],["British","NORP"],["Midland","GPE"],["737","PRODUCT"],["East Midlands Airport","FAC"],["47","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 10 – In accordance with United Nations Security Council Resolution 626 and the New York Accords, Cuban troops begin withdrawing from Angola.","links":["/wiki/January_10","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council_Resolution_626","/wiki/Tripartite_Accord_(Angola)","/wiki/Cuba","/wiki/Angola"],"ents":[["January 10 –","DATE"],["United Nations Security Council Resolution 626","ORG"],["the New York Accords","ORG"],["Cuban","NORP"],["Angola","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 11 - President of the United States Ronald Reagan delivers his farewell address to the nation.","links":["/wiki/Ronald_Reagan"],"ents":[["January 11 - President of","DATE"],["the United States","GPE"],["Ronald Reagan","PERSON"]]},{"text":"January 11 - The Lexus and Infiniti luxury car brands are launched at the North American International Auto Show in Detroit with the unveiling of the 1990 Lexus LS and Infiniti Q45 sedans.","links":["/wiki/Lexus","/wiki/Infiniti","/wiki/North_American_International_Auto_Show","/wiki/Lexus_LS","/wiki/Infiniti_Q45"],"ents":[["January 11 - The","DATE"],["Lexus","ORG"],["Infiniti","ORG"],["North American International Auto Show","EVENT"],["Detroit","GPE"],["1990","DATE"],["Lexus","ORG"],["Infiniti","ORG"],["Q45","PRODUCT"]]},{"text":"January 15 - Thirty-five European nations, meeting in Vienna, agree to strengthen human rights and strengthen East-West trade.","links":["/wiki/Vienna","/wiki/Human_rights"],"ents":[["January 15 - Thirty - five","DATE"],["European","NORP"],["Vienna","GPE"],["East - West trade","LOC"]]},{"text":"January 15 - \"Palach Week\": A pro-democracy demonstration in Prague is attacked by the police.[5]","links":["/wiki/Jan_Palach#Posthumous_recognition","/wiki/Prague","#cite_note-Revolutionary_Year-5"],"ents":[["January 15 - \" Palach Week","DATE"],["Prague","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 17 – Stockton schoolyard shooting: Patrick Edward Purdy kills 5 children, wounds 30 and then shoots himself in Stockton, California.","links":["/wiki/January_17","/wiki/Stockton_schoolyard_shooting","/wiki/Stockton,_California"],"ents":[["January 17 – Stockton","DATE"],["Patrick Edward Purdy","PERSON"],["5","CARDINAL"],["30","CARDINAL"],["Stockton","GPE"],["California","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 18 - The Polish United Workers' Party votes to legalize Solidarity.","links":["/wiki/Polish_United_Workers%27_Party","/wiki/Solidarity_(Polish_trade_union)"],"ents":[["January 18 - The","DATE"],["United Workers ' Party","ORG"],["Solidarity","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 18 - Ante Marković succeeds Branko Mikulić as Prime Minister of Yugoslavia.","links":["/wiki/Ante_Markovi%C4%87","/wiki/Branko_Mikuli%C4%87","/wiki/Prime_Minister_of_Yugoslavia"],"ents":[["January 18 - Ante","DATE"],["Branko Mikulić","PERSON"],["Yugoslavia","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 20 – George H. W. Bush is sworn in as the 41st President of the United States.","links":["/wiki/January_20","/wiki/George_H._W._Bush","/wiki/Inauguration_of_George_H._W._Bush"],"ents":[["January 20 – George H. W. Bush","DATE"],["the United States","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 23 – A powerful earthquake in the Tajik Soviet Socialist Republic kills around 275 people.","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/1989_Gissar_earthquake","/wiki/Tajik_Soviet_Socialist_Republic"],"ents":[["January 23 –","DATE"],["the Tajik Soviet Socialist Republic","ORG"],["275","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 23–24 – Armed civilian leftists briefly attack and occupy an Argentinian army base near Buenos Aires.","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/January_24","/wiki/1989_attack_on_La_Tablada_Regiment","/wiki/Argentina","/wiki/Buenos_Aires"],"ents":[["January 23–24 – Armed","DATE"],["Argentinian","NORP"],["Buenos Aires","PERSON"]]},{"text":"January 24 – Florida executes Ted Bundy by electric chair for the murders of young women.","links":["/wiki/January_24","/wiki/Ted_Bundy"],"ents":[["January 24 – Florida","DATE"],["Ted Bundy","PERSON"]]},{"text":"January 29 – The British children's television show, Thomas & Friends, begins airing in the U.S. with the series premiere of Shining Time Station on PBS.","links":["/wiki/January_29","/wiki/Thomas_%26_Friends","/wiki/Shining_Time_Station","/wiki/PBS"],"ents":[["January 29","DATE"],["British","NORP"],["Thomas & Friends","ORG"],["U.S.","GPE"],["Shining Time Station","ORG"],["PBS","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 30 – Prime Mi