{"video_id":"JFpanWNgfQY","captions":{"sents":["Syria's war is mess.","After 6 years The conflict is divided between multiple sides, each side with foreign backers and those foreign backers dont even agree with eachother on who they are fighting for and who they are fighting against.","Now, Syria’s use of chemical weapons has provoked President Donald Trump to directly attack Syrian President Bashar Al Assad.","This is a major shift because the US has for years only focused on fighting ISIS.","To understand the criss-crossing interventions and battle lines in Syria today, and how it got this way, it helps to go back to the beginning and watch how it unfolded.","The first shots in the war are fired, in March 2011, by Syrian dictator Bashar al-Assad against peaceful Arab Spring demonstrators.","The protests grow, as do Assad's increasingly violent crackdowns.","In July the protesters start shooting back, and some Syrian troops even join them.","They call themselves the Free Syrian Army and the uprising becomes a civil war.","Extremists from around the region start traveling to Syria to join the rebels.","Assad actually encourages this by releasing jihadist prisoners to tinge the rebellion with extremism make it harder for foreign backers to supor them.","In January 2012, al-Qaeda forms a new branch in Syria, Jabhat al-Nusra.","Aso around then Syrian Kurdish groups, who had long sought autonomy take up arms and informally secede from Assad's rule in the north.","That summer is when Syria becomes a proxy war.","Iran, Assad's most important ally, intervenes on his behalf.","By the end of 2012, Iran is sending daily cargo flights and has hundreds of officers on the ground.","At the same time, the oil-rich Arab states on the Persian Gulf begin sending money and weapons to the rebels, mainly to counter Iran’s influence.","Iran steps up its influence in mid-2012 when Hezbollah, a Lebanese militia backed by Iran, invades to fight alongside Assad.","The Gulf states, especially Saudi Arabia, respond with sending more money and weapons to the rebels, this time through Jordan who also opposes Assad.","By 2013, the middle east is divided between sunni powers generally supporting the rebels andSshias generally supporting Assad That April, the Obama administration, horrified by Assad's atrocities and the mounting death toll, signs a secret order authorizing the CIA to train and equip Syrian rebels.","But the program stalls.","At the same time, The US quietly urges Arab Gulf states to stop funding extremists, but the requests go unheeded.","In August the Assad regime uses chemical weapons, provoking condemnation around the world Obama: \"Men, women, and children lying in rows – killed by poison gas...\" It is in the national security interests of the United States to respond to the Assad regime's use of chemical weapons through a targeted military strike.","Russia proposed on Monday that Syria surrender control over its chemical weapons to the International Community for its eventual dismantling, to avoid a US military strike.","The US backs down under a Russia-brokered deal, but the incident establishes Syria as a great-powers dispute between America and Russia.","Just weeks later, the first American training and arms reach Syrian rebels through the earlier-authorized CIA program.","The US is now a participant.","In February 2014, something happens that transforms the war: an al-Qaeda affiliate, based mostly in Iraq, breaks away from the group over internal disagreements.","The group calls itself the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, and it becomes al-Qaeda's enemy.","ISIS mostly fights not Assad, but the other rebels and the Kurds, carving out a mini-state it calls its Caliphate.","That summer, it marches across Iraq seizing territory, galvanizing the world against it.","The opposition in Syria divides between anti-Assad rebels and ISIS, who fight one another as well.","In September, one year after the US almost bombed Assad, it begins bombing ISIS.","It's joined by a coalition of Western and MidEast states, who all also oppose Assad.","Obama: “We're moving ahead with our campaign of airstrikes against these terrorists, and we're prepared to take action against ISIL in Syria as well.","”","That summer, in July, the Pentagon launches its own program to train Syrian rebels — but only those who'll fight ISIS, not Assad.","The program fizzles, showing that America now opposes ISIS more than Assad, but that no like-minded Syrian proxy force exists.","In August, Turkey bombs Kurdish groups in Iraq and in Turkey, even as the Kurds fight ISIS in Syria, but doesn't bomb ISIS.","This got to a core problem: the US sees ISIS as its main enemy, but the US’s allies like Turkey and a lot of other MidEast states have other priorities.","The next month, in September, Russia intervenes on behalf of Assad, sending a few dozen military aircraft to a long-held Russian base in the country.","Russia says it's there to bomb ISIS, but in fact bombs anti-Assad rebels, including some backed by the US.","The next year, Donald Trump wins the White House, vowing to stay out of Syria, and signaling that Assad should be able to stay in power.","At the end of 2016, Assad, helped by Russian airpower and Iranian sponsored militias, retakes the Syrian city of Aleppo, knocking the rebels from their last remaining urban stronghold.","Then, in Spring of 2017, Assad once again uses chemical weapons against his people, killing 85, including 20 children.","Back in the US, Trump says his attitude toward Syria and Assad has “changed very much” due to the attacks.","He vows to respond.","And within days the white house launches dozens of tomahawk missiles on an airbase in Syria, attacking the Assad Regime for the first time.","This adds yet another criss crossing complication to an already multidimensional civil war.","Syria is in ruins.","Millions have fled the country and any attempt at a ceasefire has failed.","Even as Assad recaptures land, the rebellion perseveres.","And with outside countries fueling each of the groups, it’s clear that there is still no end in sight."],"ents":[[["Syria","GPE"]],[["6 years","DATE"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["Donald Trump","PERSON"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar Al Assad","PERSON"]],[["US","GPE"],["years","DATE"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["today","DATE"]],[["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"]],[["Assad","ORG"]],[["July","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"]],[["the Free Syrian Army","ORG"]],[["Syria","GPE"]],[["Assad","PERSON"]],[["January 2012","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Jabhat al - Nusra","PERSON"]],[["Syrian","NORP"],["Kurdish","NORP"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["That summer","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"]],[["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["the end of 2012","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["daily","DATE"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"]],[["Arab","NORP"],["Persian Gulf","LOC"],["Iran","GPE"]],[["Iran","GPE"],["mid-2012","DATE"],["Hezbollah","ORG"],["Lebanese","NORP"],["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["Gulf","LOC"],["Saudi Arabia","GPE"],["Jordan","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"]],[["2013","DATE"],["Assad","ORG"],["That April","DATE"],["Obama","PERSON"],["Assad","PERSON"],["CIA","ORG"],["Syrian","NORP"]],[],[["US","GPE"],["Arab Gulf","LOC"]],[["August","DATE"],["Assad","ORG"],["Obama","PERSON"],["the United States","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["Russia","GPE"],["Monday","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["the International Community","ORG"],["US","GPE"]],[["US","GPE"],["Russia","GPE"],["Syria","GPE"],["America","GPE"],["Russia","GPE"]],[["Just weeks later","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["American","NORP"],["Syrian","NORP"],["CIA","ORG"]],[["US","GPE"]],[["February 2014","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["the Islamic State of Iraq","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["al - Qaeda 's","ORG"]],[["Assad","ORG"],["Kurds","NORP"],["Caliphate","GPE"]],[["That summer","DATE"],["Iraq","GPE"]],[["Syria","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"],["one","CARDINAL"]],[["September","DATE"],["one year","DATE"],["US","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["Western","NORP"],["MidEast","LOC"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["Obama","PERSON"],["ISIL","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"]],[],[["July","DATE"],["Pentagon","ORG"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["America","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"],["Syrian","NORP"]],[["August","DATE"],["Turkey","GPE"],["Kurdish","NORP"],["Iraq","GPE"],["Turkey","GPE"],["Kurds","NORP"],["Syria","GPE"]],[["US","GPE"],["US","GPE"],["Turkey","GPE"],["MidEast","LOC"]],[["The next month","DATE"],["September","DATE"],["Russia","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"],["a few dozen","CARDINAL"],["Russian","NORP"]],[["Russia","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"],["US","GPE"]],[["The next year","DATE"],["Donald Trump","PERSON"],["the White House","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[["the end of 2016","DATE"],["Assad","ORG"],["Russian","NORP"],["Iranian","NORP"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Aleppo","GPE"]],[["Spring of 2017","DATE"],["Assad","ORG"],["85","CARDINAL"],["20","CARDINAL"]],[["US","GPE"],["Trump","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],[],[["within days","DATE"],["dozens","CARDINAL"],["Syria","GPE"],["Assad Regime","ORG"],["first","ORDINAL"]],[],[["Syria","GPE"]],[["Millions","CARDINAL"]],[["Assad","ORG"]],[]],"timestamps":["3.919","6.029","17.699","25.1","30.609","40.859","47.6","47.6","59.149","64.68","69.82","77.96","83.36","92.469","95.32","99.359","105.46","114.939","124.84","134.709","155.47","156.75","164.629","186.84","196.46","205.599","213.11","214.989","224.841","233.61","241.26","246.349","249.062","251.599","252.599","255.01","260.45","268.36","278.95","288.91","304.85","313.92","321.82","329.74","342.79","352.03","359.35","360.44","372.45","377.32","378.32","381.05","384.27"]},"heidel":{"sents":["Syria's war is mess.","After <TIMEX3 tid=\"t2\" type=\"DURATION\" value=\"P6Y\">6 years</TIMEX3> The conflict is divided between multiple sides, each side with foreign backers and those foreign backers dont even agree with eachother on who they are fighting for and who they are fighting against.","<TIMEX3 tid=\"t3\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">Now</TIMEX3>, Syria’s use of chemical weapons has provoked President Donald Trump to directly attack Syrian President Bashar Al Assad.","This is a major shift because the US has for years only focused on fighting ISIS.","To understand the criss-crossing interventions and battle lines in Syria <TIMEX3 tid=\"t4\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">today</TIMEX3>, and how it got this way, it helps to go back to the beginning and watch how it unfolded.","The first shots in the war are fired, in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t7\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011-03\">March 2011</TIMEX3>, by Syrian dictator Bashar al-Assad against peaceful Arab <TIMEX3 tid=\"t8\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011-SP\">Spring</TIMEX3> demonstrators.","The protests grow, as do Assad's increasingly violent crackdowns.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t9\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2011-07\">July</TIMEX3> the protesters start shooting back, and some Syrian troops even join them.","They call themselves the Free Syrian Army and the uprising becomes a civil war.","Extremists from around the region start traveling to Syria to join the rebels.","Assad actually encourages this by releasing jihadist prisoners to tinge the rebellion with extremism make it harder for foreign backers to supor them.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t12\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2012-01\">January 2012</TIMEX3>, al-Qaeda forms a new branch in Syria, Jabhat al-Nusra.","Aso around then Syrian Kurdish groups, who had long sought autonomy take up arms and informally secede from Assad's rule in the north.","That <TIMEX3 tid=\"t13\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2012-SU\">summer</TIMEX3> is when Syria becomes a proxy war.","Iran, Assad's most important ally, intervenes on his behalf.","By <TIMEX3 tid=\"t15\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2012\" mod=\"END\">the end of 2012</TIMEX3>, Iran is sending daily cargo flights and has hundreds of officers on the ground.","At the same time, the oil-rich Arab states on the Persian Gulf begin sending money and weapons to the rebels, mainly to counter Iran’s influence.","Iran steps up its influence in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t17\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2012\" mod=\"MID\">mid-2012</TIMEX3> when Hezbollah, a Lebanese militia backed by Iran, invades to fight alongside Assad.","The Gulf states, especially Saudi Arabia, respond with sending more money and weapons to the rebels, this time through Jordan who also opposes Assad.","By <TIMEX3 tid=\"t18\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2013\">2013</TIMEX3>, the middle east is divided between sunni powers generally supporting the rebels andSshias generally supporting Assad That <TIMEX3 tid=\"t19\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2013-04\">April</TIMEX3>, the Obama administration, horrified by Assad's atrocities and the mounting death toll, signs a secret order authorizing the CIA to train and equip Syrian rebels.","But the program stalls.","At the same time, The US quietly urges Arab Gulf states to stop funding extremists, but the requests go unheeded.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t20\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2013-08\">August</TIMEX3> the Assad regime uses chemical weapons, provoking condemnation around the world Obama: \"Men, women, and children lying in rows – killed by poison gas...\" It is in the national security interests of the United States to respond to the Assad regime's use of chemical weapons through a targeted military strike.","Russia proposed on <TIMEX3 tid=\"t21\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"XXXX-XX-XX\">Monday</TIMEX3> that Syria surrender control over its chemical weapons to the International Community for its eventual dismantling, to avoid a US military strike.","The US backs down under a Russia-brokered deal, but the incident establishes Syria as a great-powers dispute between America and Russia.","Just weeks later, the first American training and arms reach Syrian rebels through the earlier-authorized CIA program.","The US is <TIMEX3 tid=\"t22\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> a participant.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t25\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-02\">February 2014</TIMEX3>, something happens that transforms the war: an al-Qaeda affiliate, based mostly in Iraq, breaks away from the group over internal disagreements.","The group calls itself the Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, and it becomes al-Qaeda's enemy.","ISIS mostly fights not Assad, but the other rebels and the Kurds, carving out a mini-state it calls its Caliphate.","That <TIMEX3 tid=\"t26\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-SU\">summer</TIMEX3>, it marches across Iraq seizing territory, galvanizing the world against it.","The opposition in Syria divides between anti-Assad rebels and ISIS, who fight one another as well.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t27\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-09\">September</TIMEX3>, <TIMEX3 tid=\"t28\" type=\"DURATION\" value=\"P1Y\">one year</TIMEX3> after the US almost bombed Assad, it begins bombing ISIS.","It's joined by a coalition of Western and MidEast states, who all also oppose Assad.","Obama: “We're moving ahead with our campaign of airstrikes against these terrorists, and we're prepared to take action against ISIL in Syria as well.","”","That <TIMEX3 tid=\"t30\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-SU\">summer</TIMEX3>, in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t29\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-07\">July</TIMEX3>, the Pentagon launches its own program to train Syrian rebels — but only those who'll fight ISIS, not Assad.","The program fizzles, showing that America <TIMEX3 tid=\"t31\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"PRESENT_REF\">now</TIMEX3> opposes ISIS more than Assad, but that no like-minded Syrian proxy force exists.","In <TIMEX3 tid=\"t32\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-08\">August</TIMEX3>, Turkey bombs Kurdish groups in Iraq and in Turkey, even as the Kurds fight ISIS in Syria, but doesn't bomb ISIS.","This got to a core problem: the US sees ISIS as its main enemy, but the US’s allies like Turkey and a lot of other MidEast states have other priorities.","<TIMEX3 tid=\"t34\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-09\">The next month</TIMEX3>, in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t33\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2014-09\">September</TIMEX3>, Russia intervenes on behalf of Assad, sending a few dozen military aircraft to a long-held Russian base in the country.","Russia says it's there to bomb ISIS, but in fact bombs anti-Assad rebels, including some backed by the US.","<TIMEX3 tid=\"t35\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2015\">The next year</TIMEX3>, Donald Trump wins the White House, vowing to stay out of Syria, and signaling that Assad should be able to stay in power.","At <TIMEX3 tid=\"t37\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2016\" mod=\"END\">the end of 2016</TIMEX3>, Assad, helped by Russian airpower and Iranian sponsored militias, retakes the Syrian city of Aleppo, knocking the rebels from their last remaining urban stronghold.","Then, in <TIMEX3 tid=\"t40\" type=\"DATE\" value=\"2017-SP\">Spring of 2017</TIMEX3>, Assad once again uses chemical weapons against his people, killing 85, including 20 children.","Back in the US, Trump says his attitude toward Syria and Assad has “changed very much” due to the attacks.","He vows to respond.","And within days the white house launches dozens of tomahawk missiles on an airbase in Syria, attacking the Assad Regime for the first time.","This adds yet another criss crossing complication to an already multidimensional civil war.","Syria is in ruins.","Millions have fled the country and any attempt at a ceasefire has failed.","Even as Assad recaptures land, the rebellion perseveres.","And with outside countries fueling each of the groups, it’s clear that there is still no end in sight."]},"events":[[],[],[{"text":"Now","date":"PRESENT_REF","ents":{"item":[["Syria","GPE"],["Donald Trump","PERSON"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar Al Assad","PERSON"]],"before":[["6 years","DATE"]],"after":[["Syria","GPE"],["Donald Trump","PERSON"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar Al Assad","PERSON"],["US","GPE"],["years","DATE"]]},"wiki":[]}],[],[{"text":"today","date":"PRESENT_REF","ents":{"item":[["Syria","GPE"],["today","DATE"]],"before":[["US","GPE"],["years","DATE"]],"after":[["Syria","GPE"],["today","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"]]},"wiki":[]}],[{"text":"March 2011","date":"2011-03","ents":{"item":[["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"]],"before":[["Syria","GPE"],["today","DATE"]],"after":[["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"],["Assad","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"March 11 – A 9.0-magnitude earthquake and subsequent tsunami hit the east of Japan, killing 15,840 and leaving another 3,926 missing. Tsunami warnings are issued in 50 countries and territories. Emergencies are declared at four nuclear power plants affected by the quake.[14]","links":["/wiki/March_11","/wiki/2011_T%C5%8Dhoku_earthquake_and_tsunami","/wiki/Fukushima_Daiichi_nuclear_disaster","#cite_note-14"],"ents":[["March 11","DATE"],["9.0-magnitude","CARDINAL"],["Japan","GPE"],["15,840","CARDINAL"],["3,926","CARDINAL"],["Tsunami","ORG"],["50","CARDINAL"],["four","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 15 - Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa, King of Bahrain declares a three-month state of emergency as troops from the Gulf Co-operation Council are sent to quell the civil unrest.[15][16]","links":["/wiki/Hamad_bin_Isa_Al_Khalifa","/wiki/King_of_Bahrain","/wiki/State_of_emergency","/wiki/Gulf_Co-operation_Council","/wiki/Bahraini_uprising_(2011%E2%80%93present)","#cite_note-BBCBahr15Mar-15","#cite_note-16"],"ents":[["March 15 - Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa","DATE"],["Bahrain","GPE"],["three - month","DATE"],["the Gulf Co - operation Council","ORG"]]},{"text":"March 15 - Protests breakout across Syria demanding democratic reforms and the resignation of President Bashar al-Assad.[17] The government responds by killing hundreds of protesters and laying siege to various cities, beginning the Syrian Civil War.[18]","links":["/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","#cite_note-17","/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["March 15 - Protests","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"],["the Syrian Civil War","EVENT"]]},{"text":"March 17 – The United Nations Security Council votes 10–0 to create a no-fly zone over Libya in response to allegations of government aggression against civilians.[19]","links":["/wiki/March_17","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council","/wiki/Libyan_no-fly_zone","#cite_note-19"],"ents":[["March 17","DATE"],["The United Nations Security Council","ORG"],["10–0","CARDINAL"],["Libya","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 19 – In light of continuing attacks on Libyan rebels by forces in support of leader Muammar Gaddafi,[20] military intervention authorized under UNSCR 1973 begins as French fighter jets make reconnaissance flights over Libya.[21]","links":["/wiki/March_19","/wiki/Muammar_Gaddafi","#cite_note-20","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council_Resolution_1973","#cite_note-21"],"ents":[["March 19","DATE"],["Libyan","NORP"],["Muammar Gaddafi","PERSON"],["UNSCR 1973","LAW"],["French","NORP"],["Libya","GPE"]]}],"match":{"text":"March 15 - Protests breakout across Syria demanding democratic reforms and the resignation of President Bashar al-Assad.[17] The government responds by killing hundreds of protesters and laying siege to various cities, beginning the Syrian Civil War.[18]","links":["/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","#cite_note-17","/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["March 15 - Protests","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"],["the Syrian Civil War","EVENT"]],"idx":2,"score":0.3333333333333333,"wptopics":[{"href":"/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q14746872","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"},"instance_of_arr":[null],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}]}]},{"href":"/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","title":"Bashar_al-Assad","wbid":"Q44329"},{"href":"/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q178810","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]}]}],"wptopic_rel":{"part_of":[[{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8201487","label":"Category:Egyptian Revolution of 2011"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian_revolution_of_2011","start_time":"2011-01-25T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-02-11T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q29198","label":"2011 Egyptian revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8874778","label":"Category:Tunisian Revolution"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunisian_Revolution","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-01-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q46959","label":"Tunisian Revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8589467","label":"Category:Libyan Civil War (2011)"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libyan_Civil_War_(2011)","start_time":"2011-02-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-10-23T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q81545","label":"2011 Libyan Civil War"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q20678399","label":"Category:Libyan Civil War (2014–present)"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libyan_Civil_War_(2014%E2%80%93present)","start_time":"2014-05-16T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q16911838","label":"Libyan civil war (2014–)"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22674820","label":"Category:Spillover of the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spillover_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17272643","label":"spillover of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8201475","label":"Category:Yemeni Revolution"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemeni_Revolution","start_time":"2011-01-27T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-02-27T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q210005","label":"2011 Yemeni revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q6907158","label":"Category:Bahraini uprising of 2011"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bahraini_protests_of_2011%E2%80%932014","start_time":"2011-02-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q242864","label":"Bahraini protests of 2011"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8199979","label":"Category:2010–12 Algerian protests"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010%E2%80%9312_Algerian_protests","start_time":"2010-12-28T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-01-10T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q472238","label":"2010–2012 Algerian protests"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%E2%80%9313_Egyptian_protests","start_time":"2012-11-22T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-07-03T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q3720660","label":"2012–2013 Egyptian protests"}}],[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quneitra_Governorate_clashes_(2012%E2%80%9314)","start_time":"2012-11-02T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q130721","label":"Quneitra Governorate clashes (2012–present)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Tremseh","event":{"value":"Q543202","label":"Battle of Tremseh"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Douma","event":{"value":"Q630757","label":"Battle of Douma"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ras_al-Ayn","event":{"value":"Q720348","label":"Battle of Ras al-Ayn"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Idlib_(2012)","start_time":"2012-03-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-03-13T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q978261","label":"Battle of Idlib"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houla_massacre","event":{"value":"Q1137013","label":"Houla massacre"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Aleppo_(2012%E2%80%932016)","start_time":"2012-07-19T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-12-22T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q1842866","label":"Battle of Aleppo"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Damascus_(2012)","event":{"value":"Q2094032","label":"Battle of Damascus"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Azaz_(2012)","event":{"value":"Q2105475","label":"Battle of Azaz"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rojava_conflict","start_time":"2012-07-19T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q2384201","label":"Rojava conflict"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Taftanaz","start_time":"2012-04-03T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-04-05T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q2890096","label":"Battle of Taftanaz"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/April_2012_Idlib_Governorate_Operation","event":{"value":"Q4781954","label":"April 2012 Idlib Governorate Operation"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Shaddadi_(2013)","event":{"value":"Q4872359","label":"Battle of Shadadeh"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22671249","label":"Category:Foreign involvement in the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign_involvement_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q5468411","label":"foreign involvement in the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Raqqa_(March_2013)","start_time":"2013-03-02T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-03-06T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q6627360","label":"Battle of Raqqa"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Media_coverage_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q7663273","label":"media coverage of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghouta_chemical_attack","event":{"value":"Q14626794","label":"August 2013 Ghouta chemical attack"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Maaloula","start_time":"2013-09-04T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-09-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14941448","label":"Battle of Maaloula"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_al-Assal_chemical_attack","event":{"value":"Q14942764","label":"Khan al-Assal chemical attack"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian%E2%80%93Turkish_border_incidents_during_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q15817274","label":"Syrian–Turkish border incidents during the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014_Latakia_offensive","start_time":"2014-03-21T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-06-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q15977397","label":"2014 Latakia offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Hosn","event":{"value":"Q15980307","label":"Battle of Hosn"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22674820","label":"Category:Spillover of the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spillover_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17272643","label":"spillover of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Shaer_gas_field_(July_2014)","start_time":"2014-07-17T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-07-26T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17379166","label":"Battle of the Shaer gas field"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_intervention_against_ISIL","start_time":"2014-06-13T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17507684","label":"military intervention against ISIL"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Koban%C3%AE","start_time":"2014-09-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18071930","label":"Siege of Kobanî"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Op%C3%A9ration_Chammal","start_time":"2014-09-19T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18121535","label":"Opération Chammal"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22324560","label":"Category:Turkish involvement in the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_involvement_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18208094","label":"Turkish involvement in the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014_Al-Safira_offensive","event":{"value":"Q18219537","label":"Rebel As-safira offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Wadi_Deif_(2014)","event":{"value":"Q18349084","label":"2nd Siege of Wadi Deif"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_al-Hasakah_offensive","event":{"value":"Q19428973","label":"Al-Hasakah offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_al-Hasakah_offensive","event":{"value":"Q20050670","label":"Al-Hasakah offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tell_Abyad_offensive","start_time":"2015-05-01T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2015-07-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q20087579","label":"Tell Abyad offensive"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q23311350","label":"Q23311350"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_military_intervention_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2015-09-30T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q21032720","label":"Russian military intervention in the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Russian_Sukhoi_Su-24_shootdown","event":{"value":"Q21540349","label":"2015 Russian Sukhoi Su-24 shootdown"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Homs_car_bombing","event":{"value":"Q22087809","label":"Homs car bombing"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Shaddadi_offensive_(2016)","start_time":"2016-02-17T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-02-22T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q22894201","label":"Al-Shaddadi offensive (2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/February_2016_Sayyidah_Zaynab_bombings","event":{"value":"Q22918854","label":"February 2016 Sayyidah Zaynab bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/February_2016_Homs_bombings","event":{"value":"Q22924593","label":"February 2016 Homs bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Deir_ez-Zor_(2014%E2%80%9317)","start_time":"2014-07-14T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2017-09-10T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q28419687","label":"Siege of Deir ez-Zor (2014–2017)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(2017)","start_time":"2017-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q28858948","label":"Palmyra offensive (2017)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_al-Jinah_airstrike","event":{"value":"Q28983702","label":"2017 al-Jina mosque airstrike"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Shayrat_missile_strike","event":{"value":"Q29197866","label":"2017 Shayrat missile strike"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raqqa_campaign_(2012%E2%80%9313)","start_time":"2012-09-19T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-03-06T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q29258856","label":"Raqqa campaign (2012–13)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Aleppo_suicide_car_bombing","event":{"value":"Q29413569","label":"2017 Aleppo suicide car bombing"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_military_operation_in_Idlib_Governorate","start_time":"2017-10-12T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q42075415","label":"Q42075415"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Syria_campaign_(September%E2%80%93December_2017)","start_time":"2017-09-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q44812560","label":"Eastern Syria campaign"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(March_2016)","start_time":"2016-03-09T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-03-27T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23057866","label":"Palmyra offensive (March 2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_al-Qaryatayn_(March%E2%80%93April_2016)","start_time":"2016-03-03T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-04-03T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23701422","label":"Battle of al-Qaryatayn"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manbij_offensive","start_time":"2016-03-30T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23701421","label":"Manbij offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/27_July_2016_Qamishli_bombings","event":{"value":"Q26155891","label":"27 July 2016 Qamishli bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Euphrates_Shield","start_time":"2016-08-24T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q26690015","label":"Battle of Jarabulus"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber_Sycamore","event":{"value":"Q27135026","label":"Timber Sycamore"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_Dabiq_offensive","event":{"value":"Q27185813","label":"2016 Dabiq offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quneitra_offensive_(September_2016)","start_time":"2016-09-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-09-17T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27245758","label":"Quneitra offensive (September 2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raqqa_campaign_(2016%E2%80%932017)","event":{"value":"Q27761867","label":"Raqqa campaign (2016–present)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_al-Bab","start_time":"2016-12-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2017-02-23T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27915277","label":"Battle of al-Bab"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(December_2016)","start_time":"2016-12-08T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27988133","label":"Palmyra offensive (December 2016)"}},{"start_time":"2014-01-05T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-01-17T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q15689794","label":"Q15689794"}},{"event":{"value":"Q16325336","label":"Q16325336"}},{"event":{"value":"Q20653728","label":"Q20653728"}},{"event":{"value":"Q21400288","label":"Q21400288"}},{"start_time":"2016-02-11T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-02-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q22809365","label":"Q22809365"}}]]},"wptopic_sel":{"href":"/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q14746872","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"},"instance_of_arr":[null],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}]}]}},"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0.2,0.3333333333333333],[0,0],[0,0]]},{"text":"Spring","date":"2011-SP","ents":{"item":[["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"]],"before":[["Syria","GPE"],["today","DATE"]],"after":[["first","ORDINAL"],["March 2011","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["Arab Spring","ORG"],["Assad","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"March 11 – A 9.0-magnitude earthquake and subsequent tsunami hit the east of Japan, killing 15,840 and leaving another 3,926 missing. Tsunami warnings are issued in 50 countries and territories. Emergencies are declared at four nuclear power plants affected by the quake.[14]","links":["/wiki/March_11","/wiki/2011_T%C5%8Dhoku_earthquake_and_tsunami","/wiki/Fukushima_Daiichi_nuclear_disaster","#cite_note-14"],"ents":[["March 11","DATE"],["9.0-magnitude","CARDINAL"],["Japan","GPE"],["15,840","CARDINAL"],["3,926","CARDINAL"],["Tsunami","ORG"],["50","CARDINAL"],["four","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"March 15 - Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa, King of Bahrain declares a three-month state of emergency as troops from the Gulf Co-operation Council are sent to quell the civil unrest.[15][16]","links":["/wiki/Hamad_bin_Isa_Al_Khalifa","/wiki/King_of_Bahrain","/wiki/State_of_emergency","/wiki/Gulf_Co-operation_Council","/wiki/Bahraini_uprising_(2011%E2%80%93present)","#cite_note-BBCBahr15Mar-15","#cite_note-16"],"ents":[["March 15 - Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa","DATE"],["Bahrain","GPE"],["three - month","DATE"],["the Gulf Co - operation Council","ORG"]]},{"text":"March 15 - Protests breakout across Syria demanding democratic reforms and the resignation of President Bashar al-Assad.[17] The government responds by killing hundreds of protesters and laying siege to various cities, beginning the Syrian Civil War.[18]","links":["/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","#cite_note-17","/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["March 15 - Protests","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"],["the Syrian Civil War","EVENT"]]},{"text":"March 17 – The United Nations Security Council votes 10–0 to create a no-fly zone over Libya in response to allegations of government aggression against civilians.[19]","links":["/wiki/March_17","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council","/wiki/Libyan_no-fly_zone","#cite_note-19"],"ents":[["March 17","DATE"],["The United Nations Security Council","ORG"],["10–0","CARDINAL"],["Libya","GPE"]]},{"text":"March 19 – In light of continuing attacks on Libyan rebels by forces in support of leader Muammar Gaddafi,[20] military intervention authorized under UNSCR 1973 begins as French fighter jets make reconnaissance flights over Libya.[21]","links":["/wiki/March_19","/wiki/Muammar_Gaddafi","#cite_note-20","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council_Resolution_1973","#cite_note-21"],"ents":[["March 19","DATE"],["Libyan","NORP"],["Muammar Gaddafi","PERSON"],["UNSCR 1973","LAW"],["French","NORP"],["Libya","GPE"]]},{"text":"April 11 – Former Ivorian President Laurent Gbagbo is arrested in his home in Abidjan by supporters of elected President Alassane Ouattara, with support from French forces; this effectively ends the 2010–11 Ivorian crisis and civil war.[22]","links":["/wiki/April_11","/wiki/List_of_heads_of_state_of_C%C3%B4te_d%27Ivoire","/wiki/Laurent_Gbagbo","/wiki/Abidjan","/wiki/Alassane_Ouattara","/wiki/2010%E2%80%9311_Ivorian_crisis","/wiki/Second_Ivorian_Civil_War","#cite_note-22"],"ents":[["April 11 –","DATE"],["Ivorian","NORP"],["Laurent Gbagbo","PERSON"],["Abidjan","GPE"],["Alassane Ouattara","PERSON"],["French","NORP"],["2010–11","CARDINAL"],["Ivorian","NORP"]]},{"text":"April 29 – An estimated two billion people[23] watch the wedding of Prince William, Duke of Cambridge and Catherine Middleton at Westminster Abbey in London.","links":["/wiki/April_29","#cite_note-23","/wiki/Wedding_of_Prince_William_and_Catherine_Middleton","/wiki/Prince_William,_Duke_of_Cambridge","/wiki/Catherine,_Duchess_of_Cambridge","/wiki/Westminster_Abbey"],"ents":[["April 29 –","DATE"],["two billion","CARDINAL"],["Prince William","PERSON"],["Cambridge","GPE"],["Catherine Middleton","PERSON"],["Westminster Abbey","ORG"],["London","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 1 – U.S. President Barack Obama announces that Osama bin Laden, the founder and leader of the militant group Al-Qaeda, was killed on May 2, 2011 (Pakistani time, UTC+6) during an American military operation in Pakistan.[24]","links":["/wiki/May_1","/wiki/Barack_Obama","/wiki/Osama_bin_Laden","/wiki/Al-Qaeda","/wiki/Death_of_Osama_bin_Laden","/wiki/Pakistan","#cite_note-24"],"ents":[["May 1 – U.S.","DATE"],["Barack Obama","PERSON"],["Osama bin Laden","PERSON"],["Al - Qaeda","ORG"],["May 2 , 2011","DATE"],["Pakistani","NORP"],["UTC+6","GPE"],["American","NORP"],["Pakistan","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 16 – The European Union agrees to a €78 billion rescue deal for Portugal. The bailout loan will be equally split between the European Financial Stabilisation Mechanism, the European Financial Stability Facility, and the International Monetary Fund.[25]","links":["/wiki/May_16","/wiki/European_Financial_Stabilisation_Mechanism","/wiki/European_Financial_Stability_Facility","/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund","#cite_note-25"],"ents":[["May 16 –","DATE"],["The European Union","ORG"],["€","ORG"],["78","MONEY"],["Portugal","GPE"],["the European Financial Stabilisation Mechanism","ORG"],["the European Financial Stability Facility","ORG"],["the International Monetary Fund","ORG"]]},{"text":"May 21 – Grímsvötn, Iceland's most active volcano, erupted and caused disruption to air travel in Northwestern Europe.[26]","links":["/wiki/May_21","/wiki/Gr%C3%ADmsv%C3%B6tn","#cite_note-26"],"ents":[["May 21 –","DATE"],["Iceland","GPE"],["Northwestern Europe","LOC"]]},{"text":"May 26 – Former Bosnian Serb Army commander Ratko Mladić, wanted for genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity, is arrested in Serbia.[27][28]","links":["/wiki/May_26","/wiki/Bosnia","/wiki/Serb","/wiki/Ratko_Mladi%C4%87","/wiki/Serbia","#cite_note-27","#cite_note-28"],"ents":[["May 26 –","DATE"],["Bosnian Serb Army","ORG"],["Ratko Mladić","ORG"],["Serbia","GPE"]]}],"match":{"text":"March 15 - Protests breakout across Syria demanding democratic reforms and the resignation of President Bashar al-Assad.[17] The government responds by killing hundreds of protesters and laying siege to various cities, beginning the Syrian Civil War.[18]","links":["/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","#cite_note-17","/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["March 15 - Protests","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Bashar al - Assad","PERSON"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"],["the Syrian Civil War","EVENT"]],"idx":2,"score":0.3333333333333333,"wptopics":[{"href":"/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q14746872","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"},"instance_of_arr":[null],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}]}]},{"href":"/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad","title":"Bashar_al-Assad","wbid":"Q44329"},{"href":"/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q178810","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]}]}],"wptopic_rel":{"part_of":[[{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8201487","label":"Category:Egyptian Revolution of 2011"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian_revolution_of_2011","start_time":"2011-01-25T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-02-11T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q29198","label":"2011 Egyptian revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8874778","label":"Category:Tunisian Revolution"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunisian_Revolution","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-01-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q46959","label":"Tunisian Revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8589467","label":"Category:Libyan Civil War (2011)"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libyan_Civil_War_(2011)","start_time":"2011-02-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-10-23T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q81545","label":"2011 Libyan Civil War"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q20678399","label":"Category:Libyan Civil War (2014–present)"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libyan_Civil_War_(2014%E2%80%93present)","start_time":"2014-05-16T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q16911838","label":"Libyan civil war (2014–)"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22674820","label":"Category:Spillover of the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spillover_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17272643","label":"spillover of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8201475","label":"Category:Yemeni Revolution"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemeni_Revolution","start_time":"2011-01-27T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-02-27T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q210005","label":"2011 Yemeni revolution"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q6907158","label":"Category:Bahraini uprising of 2011"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bahraini_protests_of_2011%E2%80%932014","start_time":"2011-02-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q242864","label":"Bahraini protests of 2011"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8199979","label":"Category:2010–12 Algerian protests"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010%E2%80%9312_Algerian_protests","start_time":"2010-12-28T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-01-10T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q472238","label":"2010–2012 Algerian protests"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%E2%80%9313_Egyptian_protests","start_time":"2012-11-22T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-07-03T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q3720660","label":"2012–2013 Egyptian protests"}}],[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quneitra_Governorate_clashes_(2012%E2%80%9314)","start_time":"2012-11-02T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q130721","label":"Quneitra Governorate clashes (2012–present)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Tremseh","event":{"value":"Q543202","label":"Battle of Tremseh"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Douma","event":{"value":"Q630757","label":"Battle of Douma"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ras_al-Ayn","event":{"value":"Q720348","label":"Battle of Ras al-Ayn"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Idlib_(2012)","start_time":"2012-03-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-03-13T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q978261","label":"Battle of Idlib"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houla_massacre","event":{"value":"Q1137013","label":"Houla massacre"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Aleppo_(2012%E2%80%932016)","start_time":"2012-07-19T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-12-22T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q1842866","label":"Battle of Aleppo"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Damascus_(2012)","event":{"value":"Q2094032","label":"Battle of Damascus"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Azaz_(2012)","event":{"value":"Q2105475","label":"Battle of Azaz"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rojava_conflict","start_time":"2012-07-19T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q2384201","label":"Rojava conflict"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Taftanaz","start_time":"2012-04-03T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2012-04-05T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q2890096","label":"Battle of Taftanaz"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/April_2012_Idlib_Governorate_Operation","event":{"value":"Q4781954","label":"April 2012 Idlib Governorate Operation"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Shaddadi_(2013)","event":{"value":"Q4872359","label":"Battle of Shadadeh"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22671249","label":"Category:Foreign involvement in the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign_involvement_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q5468411","label":"foreign involvement in the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Raqqa_(March_2013)","start_time":"2013-03-02T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-03-06T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q6627360","label":"Battle of Raqqa"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Media_coverage_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q7663273","label":"media coverage of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghouta_chemical_attack","event":{"value":"Q14626794","label":"August 2013 Ghouta chemical attack"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Maaloula","start_time":"2013-09-04T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-09-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14941448","label":"Battle of Maaloula"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_al-Assal_chemical_attack","event":{"value":"Q14942764","label":"Khan al-Assal chemical attack"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian%E2%80%93Turkish_border_incidents_during_the_Syrian_Civil_War","event":{"value":"Q15817274","label":"Syrian–Turkish border incidents during the Syrian civil war"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014_Latakia_offensive","start_time":"2014-03-21T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-06-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q15977397","label":"2014 Latakia offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Hosn","event":{"value":"Q15980307","label":"Battle of Hosn"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22674820","label":"Category:Spillover of the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spillover_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17272643","label":"spillover of the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Shaer_gas_field_(July_2014)","start_time":"2014-07-17T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-07-26T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17379166","label":"Battle of the Shaer gas field"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_intervention_against_ISIL","start_time":"2014-06-13T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q17507684","label":"military intervention against ISIL"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Koban%C3%AE","start_time":"2014-09-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18071930","label":"Siege of Kobanî"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Op%C3%A9ration_Chammal","start_time":"2014-09-19T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18121535","label":"Opération Chammal"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q22324560","label":"Category:Turkish involvement in the Syrian Civil War"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_involvement_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q18208094","label":"Turkish involvement in the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014_Al-Safira_offensive","event":{"value":"Q18219537","label":"Rebel As-safira offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Wadi_Deif_(2014)","event":{"value":"Q18349084","label":"2nd Siege of Wadi Deif"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_al-Hasakah_offensive","event":{"value":"Q19428973","label":"Al-Hasakah offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_al-Hasakah_offensive","event":{"value":"Q20050670","label":"Al-Hasakah offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tell_Abyad_offensive","start_time":"2015-05-01T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2015-07-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q20087579","label":"Tell Abyad offensive"}},{"main_subject":{"value":"Q23311350","label":"Q23311350"},"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_military_intervention_in_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2015-09-30T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q21032720","label":"Russian military intervention in the Syrian Civil War"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Russian_Sukhoi_Su-24_shootdown","event":{"value":"Q21540349","label":"2015 Russian Sukhoi Su-24 shootdown"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Homs_car_bombing","event":{"value":"Q22087809","label":"Homs car bombing"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Shaddadi_offensive_(2016)","start_time":"2016-02-17T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-02-22T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q22894201","label":"Al-Shaddadi offensive (2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/February_2016_Sayyidah_Zaynab_bombings","event":{"value":"Q22918854","label":"February 2016 Sayyidah Zaynab bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/February_2016_Homs_bombings","event":{"value":"Q22924593","label":"February 2016 Homs bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Deir_ez-Zor_(2014%E2%80%9317)","start_time":"2014-07-14T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2017-09-10T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q28419687","label":"Siege of Deir ez-Zor (2014–2017)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(2017)","start_time":"2017-01-01T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q28858948","label":"Palmyra offensive (2017)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_al-Jinah_airstrike","event":{"value":"Q28983702","label":"2017 al-Jina mosque airstrike"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Shayrat_missile_strike","event":{"value":"Q29197866","label":"2017 Shayrat missile strike"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raqqa_campaign_(2012%E2%80%9313)","start_time":"2012-09-19T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2013-03-06T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q29258856","label":"Raqqa campaign (2012–13)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Aleppo_suicide_car_bombing","event":{"value":"Q29413569","label":"2017 Aleppo suicide car bombing"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_military_operation_in_Idlib_Governorate","start_time":"2017-10-12T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q42075415","label":"Q42075415"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Syria_campaign_(September%E2%80%93December_2017)","start_time":"2017-09-14T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q44812560","label":"Eastern Syria campaign"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(March_2016)","start_time":"2016-03-09T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-03-27T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23057866","label":"Palmyra offensive (March 2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_al-Qaryatayn_(March%E2%80%93April_2016)","start_time":"2016-03-03T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-04-03T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23701422","label":"Battle of al-Qaryatayn"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manbij_offensive","start_time":"2016-03-30T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q23701421","label":"Manbij offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/27_July_2016_Qamishli_bombings","event":{"value":"Q26155891","label":"27 July 2016 Qamishli bombings"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Euphrates_Shield","start_time":"2016-08-24T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q26690015","label":"Battle of Jarabulus"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber_Sycamore","event":{"value":"Q27135026","label":"Timber Sycamore"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_Dabiq_offensive","event":{"value":"Q27185813","label":"2016 Dabiq offensive"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quneitra_offensive_(September_2016)","start_time":"2016-09-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-09-17T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27245758","label":"Quneitra offensive (September 2016)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raqqa_campaign_(2016%E2%80%932017)","event":{"value":"Q27761867","label":"Raqqa campaign (2016–present)"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_al-Bab","start_time":"2016-12-10T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2017-02-23T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27915277","label":"Battle of al-Bab"}},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmyra_offensive_(December_2016)","start_time":"2016-12-08T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q27988133","label":"Palmyra offensive (December 2016)"}},{"start_time":"2014-01-05T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2014-01-17T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q15689794","label":"Q15689794"}},{"event":{"value":"Q16325336","label":"Q16325336"}},{"event":{"value":"Q20653728","label":"Q20653728"}},{"event":{"value":"Q21400288","label":"Q21400288"}},{"start_time":"2016-02-11T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2016-02-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q22809365","label":"Q22809365"}}]]},"wptopic_sel":{"href":"/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","title":"Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","wbid":"Q14746872","article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_uprising_phase_of_the_Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","end_time":"2011-07-29T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q14746872","label":"Civil uprising phase of the Syrian civil war"},"instance_of_arr":[null],"part_of_arr":[{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_Spring","start_time":"2010-12-18T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q33761","label":"Arab Spring"},"event_category":{"value":"Q6452880","label":"Category:Arab Spring"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q273120","label":"protest"}]},{"article":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Civil_War","start_time":"2011-03-15T00:00:00Z","event":{"value":"Q178810","label":"Syrian Civil War"},"event_category":{"value":"Q8840308","label":"Category:Syrian Civil War"},"instance_of_arr":[{"value":"Q864113","label":"proxy war"},{"value":"Q8465","label":"civil war"}]}]}},"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0.2,0.3333333333333333],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[{"text":"July","date":"2011-07","ents":{"item":[["July","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"]],"before":[["Assad","ORG"]],"after":[["July","DATE"],["Syrian","NORP"],["the Free Syrian Army","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"July 9 – South Sudan secedes from Sudan, per the result of the independence referendum held in January.[30]","links":["/wiki/July_9","/wiki/South_Sudan","/wiki/Sudan","/wiki/South_Sudanese_independence_referendum,_2011","#cite_note-30"],"ents":[["July 9 – South Sudan","DATE"],["Sudan","GPE"],["January","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 12 – The planet Neptune completes its first orbit since it was discovered in 1846.[31]","links":["/wiki/July_12","/wiki/Neptune","#cite_note-31"],"ents":[["July 12 –","DATE"],["Neptune","ORG"],["first","ORDINAL"],["1846","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 14 – South Sudan joins the United Nations as the 193rd member.[32]","links":["/wiki/July_14","/wiki/South_Sudan","/wiki/United_Nations","#cite_note-32"],"ents":[["July 14 – South Sudan","DATE"],["the United Nations","ORG"],["193rd","ORG"]]},{"text":"July 20 - Goran Hadžić is detained in Serbia, becoming the last of 161 people indicted by the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia.[33]","links":["/wiki/Goran_Had%C5%BEi%C4%87","/wiki/International_Criminal_Tribunal_for_the_former_Yugoslavia","#cite_note-33"],"ents":[["July 20 - Goran Hadžić","DATE"],["Serbia","GPE"],["161","CARDINAL"],["the International Criminal Tribunal","ORG"],["Yugoslavia","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 20 - The United Nations declares a famine in southern Somalia, the first in over 30 years.[34]","links":["/wiki/United_Nations","/wiki/2011_Horn_of_Africa_famine","/wiki/Somalia","#cite_note-34"],"ents":[["July 20 - The","DATE"],["United Nations","ORG"],["Somalia","GPE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["over 30 years","DATE"]]},{"text":"July 21 – Space Shuttle Atlantis lands successfully at Kennedy Space Center after completing STS-135, concluding NASA's Space Shuttle program.[35]","links":["/wiki/July_21","/wiki/Space_Shuttle_Atlantis","/wiki/Kennedy_Space_Center","/wiki/STS-135","/wiki/Space_Shuttle","#cite_note-landing_times-35"],"ents":[["July 21 – Space Shuttle","DATE"],["Atlantis","PRODUCT"],["Kennedy Space Center","FAC"],["NASA","ORG"],["Space Shuttle","ORG"]]},{"text":"July 31 – In Thailand over 12.8 million people are affected by severe flooding. The World Bank estimates damages at 1,440 billion baht (US$45 billion).[36] Some areas are still six feet under water, and many factory areas remained closed at the end of the year. 815[37] people are killed, with 58 of the country's 77 provinces affected.[38]","links":["/wiki/July_31","/wiki/Thailand","/wiki/2011_Thailand_floods","/wiki/World_Bank","/wiki/Thailand_baht","#cite_note-time-36","#cite_note-37","#cite_note-38"],"ents":[["July 31","DATE"],["Thailand","GPE"],["12.8 million","CARDINAL"],["The World Bank","ORG"],["1,440 billion baht","MONEY"],["US$ 45 billion","MONEY"],["six feet","QUANTITY"],["the end of the year","DATE"],["815","CARDINAL"],["58","CARDINAL"],["77","CARDINAL"]]}],"match":null,"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[],[],[{"text":"January 2012","date":"2012-01","ents":{"item":[["January 2012","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Jabhat al - Nusra","PERSON"]],"before":[["Assad","PERSON"]],"after":[["January 2012","DATE"],["al - Qaeda","ORG"],["Syria","GPE"],["Jabhat al - Nusra","PERSON"],["Syrian","NORP"],["Kurdish","NORP"],["Assad","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"January 7 – A hot air balloon crashes near Carterton, New Zealand, killing all 11 people on board.","links":["/wiki/January_7","/wiki/2012_Carterton_hot_air_balloon_crash"],"ents":[["January 7 – A","DATE"],["Carterton","GPE"],["New Zealand","GPE"],["11","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 13 – The Costa Concordia cruise ship wrecks off the western coast of Italy.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 –","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 10 – A bombing in Khyber Agency, Pakistan, kills at least 30 people and 78 others injured.","links":["/wiki/January_10","/wiki/2012_Khyber_Agency_bombing","/wiki/Khyber_Agency"],"ents":[["January 10","DATE"],["Khyber Agency","ORG"],["Pakistan","GPE"],["at least 30","CARDINAL"],["78","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 12 – Violent protests occur in Bucharest, Romania, as two-day-old demonstrations continue against President Traian Băsescu's economic austerity measures. Clashes are reported in numerous Romanian cities between protesters and law enforcement officers.","links":["/wiki/January_12","/wiki/2012_Romanian_protests","/wiki/Bucharest","/wiki/Traian_B%C4%83sescu"],"ents":[["January 12 – Violent","DATE"],["Bucharest","GPE"],["Romania","GPE"],["two - day - old","DATE"],["Traian Băsescu","PERSON"],["Romanian","NORP"]]},{"text":"January 13 - The passenger cruise ship Costa Concordia sinks off the coast of Italy due to the captain Francesco Schettino's negligence and irresponsibility. There are 32 confirmed deaths.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 - The","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"],["Francesco Schettino 's","PERSON"],["32","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 19 - The Hong Kong-based file-sharing website Megaupload is shut down by the FBI.","links":["/wiki/January_19","/wiki/Megaupload"],"ents":[["January 19 - The","DATE"],["Hong Kong","GPE"],["Megaupload","ORG"],["FBI","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 23 – Iran–European Union relations: The European Union adopts an embargo against Iran in protest of its continued effort to enrich uranium.[3]","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","/wiki/European_Union","/wiki/Embargo","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Uranium","#cite_note-3"],"ents":[["January 23 –","DATE"],["Iran – European Union","ORG"],["The European Union","ORG"],["Iran","GPE"]]}],"match":null,"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[{"text":"summer","date":"2012-SU","ents":{"item":[["That summer","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"]],"before":[["Syrian","NORP"],["Kurdish","NORP"],["Assad","ORG"]],"after":[["That summer","DATE"],["Syria","GPE"],["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"June 5–6 – The century's second and last solar transit of Venus occurs. The next pair are predicted to occur in 2117 and 2125.[18]","links":["/wiki/June_5","/wiki/June_6","/wiki/Transit_of_Venus,_2012","/wiki/Transit_of_Venus","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["June 5–6 –","DATE"],["second","ORDINAL"],["Venus","LOC"],["2117 and 2125","DATE"]]},{"text":"June 18 – Shenzhou 9, a Chinese spacecraft carrying three Chinese astronauts, including the first-ever female, docks manually with orbiting module Tiangong-1, making them the third country, after the United States and Russia, to successfully perform the mission.[19]","links":["/wiki/June_18","/wiki/Shenzhou_9","/wiki/Spacecraft","/wiki/Space_station","/wiki/Tiangong-1","#cite_note-China’s_Shenzhou-9_successfully_docks_with_Tiangong-1-19"],"ents":[["June 18 – Shenzhou 9","DATE"],["Chinese","NORP"],["three","CARDINAL"],["Chinese","NORP"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Tiangong-1","PRODUCT"],["third","ORDINAL"],["the United States","GPE"],["Russia","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 24 – Lonesome George, the last known individual of the Pinta Island tortoise subspecies, dies in Galápagos National Park, thus making the subspecies extinct.[20]","links":["/wiki/June_24","/wiki/Lonesome_George","/wiki/Pinta_Island_tortoise","/wiki/Gal%C3%A1pagos_National_Park","/wiki/Extinction","#cite_note-Lonesome_George's_Death-20"],"ents":[["June 24 – Lonesome George","DATE"],["Pinta Island","LOC"],["Galápagos National Park","LOC"]]},{"text":"July 4 – CERN announces the discovery of a new particle with properties consistent with the Higgs boson after experiments at the Large Hadron Collider.[21][22][23][24][25]","links":["/wiki/July_4","/wiki/CERN","/wiki/Higgs_boson","/wiki/Large_Hadron_Collider","#cite_note-cern1207-21","#cite_note-cms1207-22","#cite_note-atlas1207-23","#cite_note-24","#cite_note-NYT-20120704-25"],"ents":[["July 4 – CERN","DATE"],["Higgs","PERSON"],["the Large Hadron Collider","FAC"]]},{"text":"July 20 – 2012 Aurora shooting: Twelve people die and 58 are injured in a mass shooting at a movie theater in Aurora, Colorado. The shooter, James Holmes, opens fire on a crowd during a screening of The Dark Knight Rises. He is found behind the theater claiming to be \"The Joker\".[26]","links":["/wiki/July_20","/wiki/2012_Aurora_shooting","/wiki/Mass_shooting","/wiki/Aurora,_Colorado","/wiki/The_Dark_Knight_Rises","/wiki/Joker_(character)","#cite_note-26"],"ents":[["July 20 – 2012","DATE"],["Twelve","CARDINAL"],["58","CARDINAL"],["Aurora","GPE"],["Colorado","GPE"],["James Holmes","PERSON"],["The Dark Knight Rises","FAC"]]},{"text":"July 27 – August 12 – The 2012 Summer Olympics are held in London, England, United Kingdom.[27]","links":["/wiki/July_27","/wiki/August_12","/wiki/2012_Summer_Olympics","#cite_note-27"],"ents":[["July 27 – August 12 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["London","GPE"],["England","GPE"],["United Kingdom","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 30–31 – In the worst power outage in world history, the 2012 India blackouts leave 620 million people without power.[28][29][30]","links":["/wiki/July_30","/wiki/July_31","/wiki/2012_India_blackouts","#cite_note-28","#cite_note-29","#cite_note-30"],"ents":[["July 30–31 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["India","GPE"],["620 million","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"August 6 – Curiosity, the Mars Science Laboratory mission's rover, successfully lands on Mars.[31]","links":["/wiki/August_6","/wiki/Curiosity_(rover)","/wiki/Mars_Science_Laboratory","/wiki/Mars_rover","/wiki/Mars","#cite_note-MarsScienceLaboratory-31"],"ents":[["August 6 – Curiosity","DATE"],["the Mars Science Laboratory","PRODUCT"],["Mars","LOC"]]},{"text":"August 31 – Armenia severs diplomatic relations with Hungary, following the extradition to Azerbaijan and subsequent pardoning of Ramil Safarov, who was convicted of killing an Armenian soldier in Hungary in 2004. The move is also met with fierce criticism from other countries.[32]","links":["/wiki/August_31","/wiki/Armenia","/wiki/Armenia%E2%80%93Hungary_relations","/wiki/Azerbaijan","/wiki/Ramil_Safarov","#cite_note-32"],"ents":[["August 31 –","DATE"],["Armenia","GPE"],["Hungary","GPE"],["Azerbaijan","GPE"],["Ramil Safarov","PERSON"],["Armenian","NORP"],["Hungary","GPE"],["2004","DATE"]]}],"match":null,"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[{"text":"the end of 2012","date":"2012","ents":{"item":[["the end of 2012","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["daily","DATE"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"]],"before":[["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],"after":[["the end of 2012","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["daily","DATE"],["hundreds","CARDINAL"],["Arab","NORP"],["Persian Gulf","LOC"],["Iran","GPE"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"January 7 – A hot air balloon crashes near Carterton, New Zealand, killing all 11 people on board.","links":["/wiki/January_7","/wiki/2012_Carterton_hot_air_balloon_crash"],"ents":[["January 7 – A","DATE"],["Carterton","GPE"],["New Zealand","GPE"],["11","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 13 – The Costa Concordia cruise ship wrecks off the western coast of Italy.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 –","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 10 – A bombing in Khyber Agency, Pakistan, kills at least 30 people and 78 others injured.","links":["/wiki/January_10","/wiki/2012_Khyber_Agency_bombing","/wiki/Khyber_Agency"],"ents":[["January 10","DATE"],["Khyber Agency","ORG"],["Pakistan","GPE"],["at least 30","CARDINAL"],["78","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 12 – Violent protests occur in Bucharest, Romania, as two-day-old demonstrations continue against President Traian Băsescu's economic austerity measures. Clashes are reported in numerous Romanian cities between protesters and law enforcement officers.","links":["/wiki/January_12","/wiki/2012_Romanian_protests","/wiki/Bucharest","/wiki/Traian_B%C4%83sescu"],"ents":[["January 12 – Violent","DATE"],["Bucharest","GPE"],["Romania","GPE"],["two - day - old","DATE"],["Traian Băsescu","PERSON"],["Romanian","NORP"]]},{"text":"January 13 - The passenger cruise ship Costa Concordia sinks off the coast of Italy due to the captain Francesco Schettino's negligence and irresponsibility. There are 32 confirmed deaths.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 - The","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"],["Francesco Schettino 's","PERSON"],["32","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 19 - The Hong Kong-based file-sharing website Megaupload is shut down by the FBI.","links":["/wiki/January_19","/wiki/Megaupload"],"ents":[["January 19 - The","DATE"],["Hong Kong","GPE"],["Megaupload","ORG"],["FBI","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 23 – Iran–European Union relations: The European Union adopts an embargo against Iran in protest of its continued effort to enrich uranium.[3]","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","/wiki/European_Union","/wiki/Embargo","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Uranium","#cite_note-3"],"ents":[["January 23 –","DATE"],["Iran – European Union","ORG"],["The European Union","ORG"],["Iran","GPE"]]},{"text":"February 6 – The Diamond Jubilee of Queen Elizabeth II marks the 60th anniversary of her accession to the thrones of the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand, and the 60th anniversary of her becoming Head of the Commonwealth.[4][5]","links":["/wiki/February_6","/wiki/Diamond_Jubilee_of_Elizabeth_II","/wiki/United_Kingdom","/wiki/Canada","/wiki/Australia","/wiki/New_Zealand","/wiki/Head_of_the_Commonwealth","#cite_note-4","#cite_note-5"],"ents":[["February 6 –","DATE"],["Queen Elizabeth II","PERSON"],["60th","ORDINAL"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Australia","GPE"],["New Zealand","GPE"],["60th","ORDINAL"],["Commonwealth","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 19 – Iran suspends oil exports to Britain and France, following sanctions put in place by the European Union and the United States in January.[6]","links":["/wiki/February_19","/wiki/Iran","#cite_note-6"],"ents":[["February 19 – Iran","DATE"],["Britain","GPE"],["France","GPE"],["the European Union","ORG"],["the United States","GPE"],["January","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 21 – Greek government-debt crisis: Eurozone finance ministers reach an agreement on a second, €130-billion Greek bailout.[7]","links":["/wiki/February_21","/wiki/Greek_government-debt_crisis","/wiki/Eurozone","/wiki/Euro","/wiki/Bailout","#cite_note-7"],"ents":[["February 21","DATE"],["second","ORDINAL"],["130-billion","MONEY"],["Greek","NORP"]]},{"text":"March 13 – After 246 years since its first publication, the Encyclopædia Britannica discontinues its print edition.[8]","links":["/wiki/March_13","/wiki/Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica","#cite_note-8"],"ents":[["March 13 –","DATE"],["246 years","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Encyclopædia Britannica","PERSON"]]},{"text":"March 22 – The President of Mali, Amadou Toumani Touré, is ousted in a coup d'état after mutinous soldiers attack government offices.[9]","links":["/wiki/March_22","/wiki/List_of_heads_of_state_of_Mali","/wiki/Amadou_Toumani_Tour%C3%A9","/wiki/2012_Malian_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","#cite_note-9"],"ents":[["March 22 –","DATE"],["Mali","PERSON"],["Amadou Toumani Touré","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 6 – The National Movement for the Liberation of Azawad unilaterally declares the independence of Azawad from Mali.[10]","links":["/wiki/April_6","/wiki/National_Movement_for_the_Liberation_of_Azawad","/wiki/Azawad","/wiki/Mali","#cite_note-10"],"ents":[["April 6 –","DATE"],["The National Movement for the Liberation","ORG"],["Azawad","PERSON"],["Azawad","PERSON"],["Mali","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 12 – Mutinous soldiers in Guinea-Bissau stage a coup d'état and take control of the capital city, Bissau. They arrest interim President Raimundo Pereira and leading presidential candidate Carlos Gomes Júnior in the midst of a presidential election campaign.[11]","links":["/wiki/April_12","/wiki/Mutiny","/wiki/Guinea-Bissau","/wiki/2012_Guinea-Bissau_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","/wiki/Bissau","/wiki/Raimundo_Pereira","/wiki/Carlos_Gomes_J%C3%BAnior","/wiki/Guinea-Bissau_presidential_election,_2012","#cite_note-ap-11"],"ents":[["April 12 – Mutinous","DATE"],["Guinea","GPE"],["Bissau","GPE"],["Raimundo Pereira","PERSON"],["Carlos Gomes Júnior","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 13 – Kwangmyŏngsŏng-3, a North Korean Earth observation satellite, explodes shortly after launch. The United States and other countries had called the impending launch a violation of United Nations Security Council demands.[12] The launch was planned to mark the centenary of the birth of Kim Il-sung, the founder of the republic.[12]","links":["/wiki/April_13","/wiki/Kwangmy%C5%8Fngs%C5%8Fng-3","/wiki/North_Korea","/wiki/Earth_observation_satellite","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council","#cite_note-NK_satellite-12","/wiki/Kim_Il-sung","#cite_note-NK_satellite-12"],"ents":[["April 13 – Kwangmyŏngsŏng-3","DATE"],["North Korean Earth","NORP"],["The United States","GPE"],["United Nations Security Council","ORG"],["Kim Il - sung","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 26 – Former Liberian President Charles Taylor is found guilty on 11 counts of aiding and abetting war crimes and crimes against humanity during the Sierra Leone Civil War.[13]","links":["/wiki/April_26","/wiki/Liberia","/wiki/Charles_Taylor_(Liberian_politician)","/wiki/Sierra_Leone_Civil_War","#cite_note-13"],"ents":[["April 26 –","DATE"],["Liberian","NORP"],["Charles Taylor","PERSON"],["11","CARDINAL"],["the Sierra Leone Civil War","ORG"]]},{"text":"May 2 – A pastel version of The Scream, by the Norwegian painter Edvard Munch, sells for US$120 million in a New York City auction, setting a new world record for an auctioned work of art.[14][15]","links":["/wiki/May_2","/wiki/Pastel","/wiki/The_Scream","/wiki/Edvard_Munch","#cite_note-14","#cite_note-15"],"ents":[["May 2 –","DATE"],["Norwegian","NORP"],["Edvard Munch","PERSON"],["US$ 120 million","MONEY"],["New York City","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 12 – August 12 – The 2012 World Expo takes place in Yeosu, South Korea.[16]","links":["/wiki/May_12","/wiki/August_12","/wiki/Expo_2012","/wiki/Yeosu","#cite_note-Expo_2012-16"],"ents":[["May 12 – August 12 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["World Expo","EVENT"],["Yeosu","GPE"],["South Korea","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 22 – Tokyo Skytree, the tallest self-supporting tower in the world at 634 metres high, is opened to the public.[17]","links":["/wiki/May_22","/wiki/Tokyo_Skytree","/wiki/List_of_tallest_towers_in_the_world","#cite_note-17"],"ents":[["May 22 –","DATE"],["Tokyo Skytree","ORG"],["634 metres","QUANTITY"]]},{"text":"June 5–6 – The century's second and last solar transit of Venus occurs. The next pair are predicted to occur in 2117 and 2125.[18]","links":["/wiki/June_5","/wiki/June_6","/wiki/Transit_of_Venus,_2012","/wiki/Transit_of_Venus","#cite_note-18"],"ents":[["June 5–6 –","DATE"],["second","ORDINAL"],["Venus","LOC"],["2117 and 2125","DATE"]]},{"text":"June 18 – Shenzhou 9, a Chinese spacecraft carrying three Chinese astronauts, including the first-ever female, docks manually with orbiting module Tiangong-1, making them the third country, after the United States and Russia, to successfully perform the mission.[19]","links":["/wiki/June_18","/wiki/Shenzhou_9","/wiki/Spacecraft","/wiki/Space_station","/wiki/Tiangong-1","#cite_note-China’s_Shenzhou-9_successfully_docks_with_Tiangong-1-19"],"ents":[["June 18 – Shenzhou 9","DATE"],["Chinese","NORP"],["three","CARDINAL"],["Chinese","NORP"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Tiangong-1","PRODUCT"],["third","ORDINAL"],["the United States","GPE"],["Russia","GPE"]]},{"text":"June 24 – Lonesome George, the last known individual of the Pinta Island tortoise subspecies, dies in Galápagos National Park, thus making the subspecies extinct.[20]","links":["/wiki/June_24","/wiki/Lonesome_George","/wiki/Pinta_Island_tortoise","/wiki/Gal%C3%A1pagos_National_Park","/wiki/Extinction","#cite_note-Lonesome_George's_Death-20"],"ents":[["June 24 – Lonesome George","DATE"],["Pinta Island","LOC"],["Galápagos National Park","LOC"]]},{"text":"July 4 – CERN announces the discovery of a new particle with properties consistent with the Higgs boson after experiments at the Large Hadron Collider.[21][22][23][24][25]","links":["/wiki/July_4","/wiki/CERN","/wiki/Higgs_boson","/wiki/Large_Hadron_Collider","#cite_note-cern1207-21","#cite_note-cms1207-22","#cite_note-atlas1207-23","#cite_note-24","#cite_note-NYT-20120704-25"],"ents":[["July 4 – CERN","DATE"],["Higgs","PERSON"],["the Large Hadron Collider","FAC"]]},{"text":"July 20 – 2012 Aurora shooting: Twelve people die and 58 are injured in a mass shooting at a movie theater in Aurora, Colorado. The shooter, James Holmes, opens fire on a crowd during a screening of The Dark Knight Rises. He is found behind the theater claiming to be \"The Joker\".[26]","links":["/wiki/July_20","/wiki/2012_Aurora_shooting","/wiki/Mass_shooting","/wiki/Aurora,_Colorado","/wiki/The_Dark_Knight_Rises","/wiki/Joker_(character)","#cite_note-26"],"ents":[["July 20 – 2012","DATE"],["Twelve","CARDINAL"],["58","CARDINAL"],["Aurora","GPE"],["Colorado","GPE"],["James Holmes","PERSON"],["The Dark Knight Rises","FAC"]]},{"text":"July 27 – August 12 – The 2012 Summer Olympics are held in London, England, United Kingdom.[27]","links":["/wiki/July_27","/wiki/August_12","/wiki/2012_Summer_Olympics","#cite_note-27"],"ents":[["July 27 – August 12 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["London","GPE"],["England","GPE"],["United Kingdom","GPE"]]},{"text":"July 30–31 – In the worst power outage in world history, the 2012 India blackouts leave 620 million people without power.[28][29][30]","links":["/wiki/July_30","/wiki/July_31","/wiki/2012_India_blackouts","#cite_note-28","#cite_note-29","#cite_note-30"],"ents":[["July 30–31 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["India","GPE"],["620 million","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"August 6 – Curiosity, the Mars Science Laboratory mission's rover, successfully lands on Mars.[31]","links":["/wiki/August_6","/wiki/Curiosity_(rover)","/wiki/Mars_Science_Laboratory","/wiki/Mars_rover","/wiki/Mars","#cite_note-MarsScienceLaboratory-31"],"ents":[["August 6 – Curiosity","DATE"],["the Mars Science Laboratory","PRODUCT"],["Mars","LOC"]]},{"text":"August 31 – Armenia severs diplomatic relations with Hungary, following the extradition to Azerbaijan and subsequent pardoning of Ramil Safarov, who was convicted of killing an Armenian soldier in Hungary in 2004. The move is also met with fierce criticism from other countries.[32]","links":["/wiki/August_31","/wiki/Armenia","/wiki/Armenia%E2%80%93Hungary_relations","/wiki/Azerbaijan","/wiki/Ramil_Safarov","#cite_note-32"],"ents":[["August 31 –","DATE"],["Armenia","GPE"],["Hungary","GPE"],["Azerbaijan","GPE"],["Ramil Safarov","PERSON"],["Armenian","NORP"],["Hungary","GPE"],["2004","DATE"]]},{"text":"September 7 – Canada officially cuts diplomatic ties with Iran by closing its embassy in Tehran, and orders the expulsion of Iranian diplomats from Ottawa, over support for Syria, nuclear plans and human rights abuses.[33]","links":["/wiki/September_7","/wiki/Canada%E2%80%93Iran_relations","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Tehran","/wiki/Ottawa","/wiki/Syria","#cite_note-33"],"ents":[["September 7 – Canada","DATE"],["Iran","GPE"],["Tehran","GPE"],["Iranian","NORP"],["Ottawa","GPE"],["Syria","GPE"]]},{"text":"September 11–27 – A series of terrorist attacks are directed against United States diplomatic missions worldwide, as well as diplomatic missions of Germany, Switzerland and the United Kingdom. In the US, opinions are divided over whether the attacks are a reaction to a YouTube trailer for the film Innocence of Muslims. In Libya, among the dead is US ambassador J. Christopher Stevens.[34][35][36][37][38]","links":["/wiki/September_11","/wiki/September_27","/wiki/Reactions_to_Innocence_of_Muslims","/wiki/YouTube","/wiki/Innocence_of_Muslims","/wiki/United_States_Ambassador_to_Libya","/wiki/J._Christopher_Stevens","#cite_note-34","#cite_note-35","#cite_note-36","#cite_note-37","#cite_note-38"],"ents":[["September","DATE"],["11–27","CARDINAL"],["United States","GPE"],["Germany","GPE"],["Switzerland","GPE"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"],["US","GPE"],["YouTube","NORP"],["Innocence of Muslims","WORK_OF_ART"],["Libya","GPE"],["US","GPE"],["J. Christopher Stevens","PERSON"]]},{"text":"October 14 – Austrian skydiver Felix Baumgartner becomes the first person to break the sound barrier without any machine assistance during a record space dive out of the Red Bull Stratos helium-filled balloon from 24 miles (39 kilometers) over Roswell, New Mexico in the United States.[39][40][41]","links":["/wiki/October_14","/wiki/Skydiver","/wiki/Felix_Baumgartner","/wiki/Sound_barrier","/wiki/Space_diving","/wiki/Red_Bull_Stratos","/wiki/Helium","/wiki/Roswell,_New_Mexico","#cite_note-39","#cite_note-40","#cite_note-41"],"ents":[["October 14 –","DATE"],["Felix Baumgartner","PERSON"],["first","ORDINAL"],["the Red Bull Stratos","FAC"],["24 miles","QUANTITY"],["39 kilometers","QUANTITY"],["Roswell","PERSON"],["New Mexico","GPE"],["the United States","GPE"]]},{"text":"October 16 – Seven paintings worth $25 million are stolen from the Kunsthal in Rotterdam, the Netherlands.[42][43][44][45]","links":["/wiki/October_16","/wiki/Kunsthal","/wiki/Rotterdam","#cite_note-42","#cite_note-43","#cite_note-44","#cite_note-45"],"ents":[["October 16 – Seven","DATE"],["$ 25 million","MONEY"],["the Kunsthal in Rotterdam","ORG"],["the Netherlands","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 13 - A total solar eclipse occurred in parts of Australia and the South Pacific.","links":["/wiki/November_13"],"ents":[["November 13 - A","DATE"],["Australia","GPE"],["the South Pacific","LOC"]]},{"text":"November 14–21 – Israel launches Operation Pillar of Defense against the Palestinian-governed Gaza Strip, killing Hamas military chief Ahmed Jabari. In the following week 140 Palestinians and five Israelis are killed in an ensuing cycle of violence. A ceasefire between Israel and Hamas is announced by Egyptian Foreign Minister Mohamed Kamel Amr and US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton after the week-long escalation in hostilities in Southern Israel and the Gaza Strip.[46][47][48][49][50]","links":["/wiki/November_14","/wiki/November_21","/wiki/Israel","/wiki/Operation_Pillar_of_Defense","/wiki/Palestinian_people","/wiki/Gaza_Strip","/wiki/Hamas","/wiki/Ahmed_Jabari","/wiki/Egyptian_Foreign_Minister","/wiki/Mohamed_Kamel_Amr","/wiki/US_Secretary_of_State","/wiki/Hillary_Clinton","/wiki/Southern_District_(Israel)","#cite_note-AJE-46","#cite_note-enews-47","#cite_note-48","#cite_note-49","#cite_note-50"],"ents":[["November 14–21 – Israel","DATE"],["Palestinian","NORP"],["Gaza Strip","GPE"],["Hamas","ORG"],["Ahmed Jabari","PERSON"],["the following week","DATE"],["140","CARDINAL"],["Palestinians","NORP"],["five","CARDINAL"],["Israelis","NORP"],["Israel","GPE"],["Hamas","ORG"],["Egyptian","NORP"],["Mohamed Kamel Amr","PERSON"],["US","GPE"],["State","ORG"],["Hillary Clinton","PERSON"],["week - long","DATE"],["Southern Israel","LOC"],["the Gaza Strip","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 25 – December 9 – Typhoon Bopha, known as \"Pablo\" in the Philippines, kills at least 1,067 with around 838 people still missing. The typhoon causes considerable damage in the island of Mindanao.[51][52][53]","links":["/wiki/November_25","/wiki/December_9","/wiki/Typhoon_Bopha","/wiki/Mindanao","#cite_note-51","#cite_note-52","#cite_note-53"],"ents":[["November 25 – December 9 – Typhoon Bopha","DATE"],["Pablo","WORK_OF_ART"],["Philippines","GPE"],["at least 1,067","CARDINAL"],["838","CARDINAL"],["Mindanao","GPE"]]},{"text":"November 29 – The UN General Assembly approves a motion granting Palestine non-member observer state status.[54]","links":["/wiki/November_29","/wiki/United_Nations_General_Assembly","/wiki/United_Nations_General_Assembly_resolution_67/19","/wiki/State_of_Palestine","/wiki/United_Nations_General_Assembly_observers","#cite_note-time-54"],"ents":[["November 29 –","DATE"],["The UN General Assembly","ORG"],["Palestine","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 8 – In Qatar, the UN Climate Change Conference agrees to extend the Kyoto Protocol until 2020.[55]","links":["/wiki/December_8","/wiki/Qatar","/wiki/2012_United_Nations_Climate_Change_Conference","/wiki/Kyoto_Protocol","#cite_note-55"],"ents":[["December 8 –","DATE"],["Qatar","GPE"],["the UN Climate Change Conference","ORG"],["the Kyoto Protocol","LAW"],["2020","DATE"]]},{"text":"December 14 – Sandy Hook Elementary School shooting: Twenty-eight people, including the gunman, are killed in Sandy Hook, Connecticut.","links":["/wiki/December_14","/wiki/Sandy_Hook_Elementary_School_shooting"],"ents":[["December 14 –","DATE"],["Twenty - eight","CARDINAL"],["Sandy Hook","PERSON"],["Connecticut","GPE"]]},{"text":"December 19 - Park Geun-hye is elected the first female president of South Korea.","links":["/wiki/December_19","/wiki/Park_Geun-hye"],"ents":[["December 19","DATE"],["Park Geun","ORG"],["first","ORDINAL"],["South Korea","GPE"]]}],"match":{"text":"January 23 – Iran–European Union relations: The European Union adopts an embargo against Iran in protest of its continued effort to enrich uranium.[3]","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","/wiki/European_Union","/wiki/Embargo","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Uranium","#cite_note-3"],"ents":[["January 23 –","DATE"],["Iran – European Union","ORG"],["The European Union","ORG"],["Iran","GPE"]],"idx":6,"score":0.3333333333333333,"wptopics":[{"href":"/wiki/January_23","title":"January_23","wbid":"Q2276"},{"href":"/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","title":"Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","wbid":null},{"href":"/wiki/European_Union","title":"European_Union","wbid":"Q458"},{"href":"/wiki/Embargo","title":"Embargo","wbid":"Q1248258"},{"href":"/wiki/Iran","title":"Iran","wbid":"Q794"},{"href":"/wiki/Uranium","title":"Uranium","wbid":"Q1098"}],"wptopic_rel":null,"wptopic_sel":null},"scores":[[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0.3333333333333333,0.16666666666666666],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0.2,0.125],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0],[0,0]]}],[],[{"text":"mid-2012","date":"2012","ents":{"item":[["Iran","GPE"],["mid-2012","DATE"],["Hezbollah","ORG"],["Lebanese","NORP"],["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"]],"before":[["Arab","NORP"],["Persian Gulf","LOC"],["Iran","GPE"]],"after":[["Iran","GPE"],["mid-2012","DATE"],["Hezbollah","ORG"],["Lebanese","NORP"],["Iran","GPE"],["Assad","ORG"],["Gulf","LOC"],["Saudi Arabia","GPE"],["Jordan","GPE"],["Assad","PERSON"]]},"wiki":[{"text":"January 7 – A hot air balloon crashes near Carterton, New Zealand, killing all 11 people on board.","links":["/wiki/January_7","/wiki/2012_Carterton_hot_air_balloon_crash"],"ents":[["January 7 – A","DATE"],["Carterton","GPE"],["New Zealand","GPE"],["11","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 13 – The Costa Concordia cruise ship wrecks off the western coast of Italy.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 –","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"]]},{"text":"January 10 – A bombing in Khyber Agency, Pakistan, kills at least 30 people and 78 others injured.","links":["/wiki/January_10","/wiki/2012_Khyber_Agency_bombing","/wiki/Khyber_Agency"],"ents":[["January 10","DATE"],["Khyber Agency","ORG"],["Pakistan","GPE"],["at least 30","CARDINAL"],["78","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 12 – Violent protests occur in Bucharest, Romania, as two-day-old demonstrations continue against President Traian Băsescu's economic austerity measures. Clashes are reported in numerous Romanian cities between protesters and law enforcement officers.","links":["/wiki/January_12","/wiki/2012_Romanian_protests","/wiki/Bucharest","/wiki/Traian_B%C4%83sescu"],"ents":[["January 12 – Violent","DATE"],["Bucharest","GPE"],["Romania","GPE"],["two - day - old","DATE"],["Traian Băsescu","PERSON"],["Romanian","NORP"]]},{"text":"January 13 - The passenger cruise ship Costa Concordia sinks off the coast of Italy due to the captain Francesco Schettino's negligence and irresponsibility. There are 32 confirmed deaths.","links":["/wiki/January_13","/wiki/Costa_Concordia"],"ents":[["January 13 - The","DATE"],["Costa Concordia","GPE"],["Italy","GPE"],["Francesco Schettino 's","PERSON"],["32","CARDINAL"]]},{"text":"January 19 - The Hong Kong-based file-sharing website Megaupload is shut down by the FBI.","links":["/wiki/January_19","/wiki/Megaupload"],"ents":[["January 19 - The","DATE"],["Hong Kong","GPE"],["Megaupload","ORG"],["FBI","ORG"]]},{"text":"January 23 – Iran–European Union relations: The European Union adopts an embargo against Iran in protest of its continued effort to enrich uranium.[3]","links":["/wiki/January_23","/wiki/Iran%E2%80%93European_Union_relations","/wiki/European_Union","/wiki/Embargo","/wiki/Iran","/wiki/Uranium","#cite_note-3"],"ents":[["January 23 –","DATE"],["Iran – European Union","ORG"],["The European Union","ORG"],["Iran","GPE"]]},{"text":"February 6 – The Diamond Jubilee of Queen Elizabeth II marks the 60th anniversary of her accession to the thrones of the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand, and the 60th anniversary of her becoming Head of the Commonwealth.[4][5]","links":["/wiki/February_6","/wiki/Diamond_Jubilee_of_Elizabeth_II","/wiki/United_Kingdom","/wiki/Canada","/wiki/Australia","/wiki/New_Zealand","/wiki/Head_of_the_Commonwealth","#cite_note-4","#cite_note-5"],"ents":[["February 6 –","DATE"],["Queen Elizabeth II","PERSON"],["60th","ORDINAL"],["the United Kingdom","GPE"],["Canada","GPE"],["Australia","GPE"],["New Zealand","GPE"],["60th","ORDINAL"],["Commonwealth","ORG"]]},{"text":"February 19 – Iran suspends oil exports to Britain and France, following sanctions put in place by the European Union and the United States in January.[6]","links":["/wiki/February_19","/wiki/Iran","#cite_note-6"],"ents":[["February 19 – Iran","DATE"],["Britain","GPE"],["France","GPE"],["the European Union","ORG"],["the United States","GPE"],["January","DATE"]]},{"text":"February 21 – Greek government-debt crisis: Eurozone finance ministers reach an agreement on a second, €130-billion Greek bailout.[7]","links":["/wiki/February_21","/wiki/Greek_government-debt_crisis","/wiki/Eurozone","/wiki/Euro","/wiki/Bailout","#cite_note-7"],"ents":[["February 21","DATE"],["second","ORDINAL"],["130-billion","MONEY"],["Greek","NORP"]]},{"text":"March 13 – After 246 years since its first publication, the Encyclopædia Britannica discontinues its print edition.[8]","links":["/wiki/March_13","/wiki/Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica","#cite_note-8"],"ents":[["March 13 –","DATE"],["246 years","DATE"],["first","ORDINAL"],["Encyclopædia Britannica","PERSON"]]},{"text":"March 22 – The President of Mali, Amadou Toumani Touré, is ousted in a coup d'état after mutinous soldiers attack government offices.[9]","links":["/wiki/March_22","/wiki/List_of_heads_of_state_of_Mali","/wiki/Amadou_Toumani_Tour%C3%A9","/wiki/2012_Malian_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","#cite_note-9"],"ents":[["March 22 –","DATE"],["Mali","PERSON"],["Amadou Toumani Touré","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 6 – The National Movement for the Liberation of Azawad unilaterally declares the independence of Azawad from Mali.[10]","links":["/wiki/April_6","/wiki/National_Movement_for_the_Liberation_of_Azawad","/wiki/Azawad","/wiki/Mali","#cite_note-10"],"ents":[["April 6 –","DATE"],["The National Movement for the Liberation","ORG"],["Azawad","PERSON"],["Azawad","PERSON"],["Mali","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 12 – Mutinous soldiers in Guinea-Bissau stage a coup d'état and take control of the capital city, Bissau. They arrest interim President Raimundo Pereira and leading presidential candidate Carlos Gomes Júnior in the midst of a presidential election campaign.[11]","links":["/wiki/April_12","/wiki/Mutiny","/wiki/Guinea-Bissau","/wiki/2012_Guinea-Bissau_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat","/wiki/Bissau","/wiki/Raimundo_Pereira","/wiki/Carlos_Gomes_J%C3%BAnior","/wiki/Guinea-Bissau_presidential_election,_2012","#cite_note-ap-11"],"ents":[["April 12 – Mutinous","DATE"],["Guinea","GPE"],["Bissau","GPE"],["Raimundo Pereira","PERSON"],["Carlos Gomes Júnior","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 13 – Kwangmyŏngsŏng-3, a North Korean Earth observation satellite, explodes shortly after launch. The United States and other countries had called the impending launch a violation of United Nations Security Council demands.[12] The launch was planned to mark the centenary of the birth of Kim Il-sung, the founder of the republic.[12]","links":["/wiki/April_13","/wiki/Kwangmy%C5%8Fngs%C5%8Fng-3","/wiki/North_Korea","/wiki/Earth_observation_satellite","/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council","#cite_note-NK_satellite-12","/wiki/Kim_Il-sung","#cite_note-NK_satellite-12"],"ents":[["April 13 – Kwangmyŏngsŏng-3","DATE"],["North Korean Earth","NORP"],["The United States","GPE"],["United Nations Security Council","ORG"],["Kim Il - sung","PERSON"]]},{"text":"April 26 – Former Liberian President Charles Taylor is found guilty on 11 counts of aiding and abetting war crimes and crimes against humanity during the Sierra Leone Civil War.[13]","links":["/wiki/April_26","/wiki/Liberia","/wiki/Charles_Taylor_(Liberian_politician)","/wiki/Sierra_Leone_Civil_War","#cite_note-13"],"ents":[["April 26 –","DATE"],["Liberian","NORP"],["Charles Taylor","PERSON"],["11","CARDINAL"],["the Sierra Leone Civil War","ORG"]]},{"text":"May 2 – A pastel version of The Scream, by the Norwegian painter Edvard Munch, sells for US$120 million in a New York City auction, setting a new world record for an auctioned work of art.[14][15]","links":["/wiki/May_2","/wiki/Pastel","/wiki/The_Scream","/wiki/Edvard_Munch","#cite_note-14","#cite_note-15"],"ents":[["May 2 –","DATE"],["Norwegian","NORP"],["Edvard Munch","PERSON"],["US$ 120 million","MONEY"],["New York City","GPE"]]},{"text":"May 12 – August 12 – The 2012 World Expo takes place in Yeosu, South Korea.[16]","links":["/wiki/May_12","/wiki/August_12","/wiki/Expo_2012","/wiki/Yeosu","#cite_note-Expo_2012-16"],"ents":[["May 12 – August 12 –","DATE"],["2012","DATE"],["World Expo","EVENT"],["Yeosu","GPE"],["South Korea","GPE"]